<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Large letters Three in number, containing much necessarie matter, for the intruction and comfort of such, as are distressed in conscience by feeling of sinne, and feare of Gods wrath. Written heeretofore by T. W. for some deare friends of his, and now published and printed for the raising vp of such as labor vnder the heauie burthen of an affected spirite.</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103076</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838834</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1161:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Large letters Three in number, containing much necessarie matter, for the intruction and comfort of such, as are distressed in conscience by feeling of sinne, and feare of Gods wrath. Written heeretofore by T. W. for some deare friends of his, and now published and printed for the raising vp of such as labor vnder the heauie burthen of an affected spirite.</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 133, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger warde, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.W. = Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 25624b on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Pages 57, 60-61, 64 and 129 misnumbered 58, 59-60, 63 and 126.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of K3, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some leaves stained and cropped at head.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fear of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:1"/>
            <p>LARGE LETTERS. Three in number, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>much neceſſarie matter,</hi> for the inſtruction and comfort of ſuch, <hi>as are diſtreſſed in conſcience by feeling of ſinne, and feare of Gods wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WRITTEN HEERETO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> by <hi>T. W.</hi> for ſome deare friends of his, and now publiſhed and printed for the raiſing vp of ſuch as labor vnder the heauie burthen of an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Spirite.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 42.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y art thou caſt downe my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within me? wait on God: for I will yet giue him thanks, hee is my preſent h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lpe and my God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Roger warde, for Thomas Man, 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO HIS FAITHFVLL friends, and verie deare brethren in</hi> Chriſt, Maſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Roger Ofield, Robert Waſhborne, George Smith, Thomas Shipton, Iohn Field, Robert Iones, Iohn Harper, Iohn Hounſell, and all the reſt of his Christian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaunce in London, as well as though they were particularlie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, together with all thoſe that els where in the land, vnfaignedly feare the Lord, and looke for the glorious appearing, of his ſonne and our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>T. W.</hi> wiſheth all ſpirituall goodnes &amp; heauenly comfort in this life, and in the end the eternall glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their bodies and ſoules, in euerlaſting bliſſe through Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y loue in the Lorde, and the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of my hart in him, haue bin in ſome meaſure of ſoundnes, (I humbly thanke God for it in Chriſt)
<pb facs="tcp:3223:3"/> ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried generallie tovvardes all the Iſraell of GOD whereſoeuer, and more particularlye tovvardes you my good Breethren: vvhereof ouer and beſides, the aſſured teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of mine owne ſoule, I haue for faithful witneſſes, the Lord himſelfe in heauen, and many of his ſaints vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth, and amongſt others you your ſelues. Cauſes leading me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are manye: but as in reſpect of God, none more powerfull, than his grace and holy ſpirite, ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into my heart: and as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of you, none more effectuall than ſundry ſincere fruites of your faith, and the comfortable feeling of the communion of ſaints, in which holy fellowſhip ſtandeth, not onely the ſpiritual felicity and good of the whole bodie, but the very ioy and contentment alſo, of euerie ſounde member therein. For outward kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that I haue receiued from you, I muſt &amp; will euerie where, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my ſelfe much beholding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:3223:3"/> you. And yet this I may vvith all boldnes profeſſe, that as that is not the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly or principall cauſe, moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to affect you: ſo though I haue beene beholding to you all, yet not to all alike, but to ſome more than to other ſome. Which alſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe not now, either to breed anie diſdaine or emulation in you, one of you towards another, for that vvere to breake the bond of charity and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the ſpirit: or to leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour though neuer ſo ſmall, that I haue receiued from you, for that wer to depriue you of your praiſe, and to declare my ſelfe ingratfull: nor craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie clavving after the maner of the vvorld, to craue newe benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, for that vvere nothing els but deceit and flatterie to procure mine own good, from all vvhich corruptions, I haue hitherto as in reſpect of my ſelfe and you, through Gods goodneſſe beene graciouſlie freed. But to let you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that your benefits haue not bene beſtowed vpon an vnskilfull or
<pb facs="tcp:3223:4"/> an thankefull perſon, but vpon ſuch a one, as by the light that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from God, hath, vveighing them in an equal ballance, eſteemed of them according to the goodnes of the gift, and the chriſtian affection of the Partie giuing. The thinges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, which haue moſt ſpeciallye lincked mee faſt in the Lorde vnto you, are your precious faith towards God, vnfaigned loue to the ſaints, chriſtian conſciences amongeſt your ſelues, and holie praiers in preſence and abſence, one of you for an other and all of you I am aſſured, for the holy cauſes and faithfull members of the whole Church, and amongeſt the reſt, euen for me pore and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am. In which duties of yours, as my heart hath greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiced in the lord, for the graces that in great mercy, he hath bin pleaſed to vouchſafe vnto you, &amp; I my ſelfe haue as in ſome ſort, though not to the ful, in regard of your ſpirituall fauours performed to me, by reſon of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3223:4"/> and wants in my ſelfe, aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them again with the like, (I write not as a vaine glorious boaſter): ſo I doubt not, but that therby God him ſelfe hath receiued glorie at your hands, his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goten much good, and you your ſelues reaped a gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meaſure and increaſe, of religy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knowledge, and dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. As for the worldly fauours that you haue ſhewed me, and bodily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites that vvay, I confeſſe my ſelfe to be far behind hand with you, and much indebted in deed, though not in affection ſurely, and readineſſe of good vvill, for ſo my heart is verie large (in humilitie I ſpeake it) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I wiſh better witneſſes of it than your ſelues, yet in regard of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvherein ſtill my griefe grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great, and increaſeth daily vpon me, as vvell by the feare that I haue of my future wants, as by the feeling of my former and preſent diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Hovvbeit, ſith thys is the Lords doing, and that he is pleaſed thereby
<pb facs="tcp:3223:5"/> to ſift me, and to ſound you (mee for my patience and comfortable indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of theſe neceſsities, and you for your faithfull obedience and vnfaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue) I can not but vvith ſome meaſure of ſpirituall ioy, vndergoe mine owne lacks, and againe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſpirites, becauſe hauing to deale vvith God and his ſeruaunts, (vvho haue learned from his holie example greater than all exception, to accept of men according to that they haue, and not according to that they haue not) I reſt reſolued, my good vvill ſhall bee accounted as a deed, ſpecially ſith I am ready euery vvhere, vvithout flatterie in my ſelf, or favvning vpon you, to acknovve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the glorie of God, and the good of his people, the great good turnes that by you, I haue receiued euen from the Lords ovvne handes. And yet gladly vvould I, if I could tell hovve, ſome vvay recompence, though not all, yet ſom part &amp; peece thereof. And in that reſpect indeede
<pb facs="tcp:3223:5"/> haue I long looked &amp; vviſhed for, as ſome good occaſion from you, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it might haue pleaſed you all, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, to haue imployed and vſed me to my pore vttermoſt: So, ſome ſufficiencie in my ſelfe, at the leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in ſome mean meaſure to haue requited that ouerflowing heape, of your kindnes and holy loue. But hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto (I deliuer it with my griefe of heart, as a man ſenſiblie ſeeing and feeling gods hand vpon my ſelfe, both that and other waies alſo) my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation and hope hath bene fruſtrat, and my power very ſhort and skant. A ſmall thing the Lorde vvas pleaſed ſome years ago, to inable me in two or three Letters, to performe for the comfort of ſome of my chriſtian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, (whoſe conflicts in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vvere great and many) which lying by mee, vvith ſome other ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thinges that I haue done, and I beeing earneſtly requeſted to make that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to many, which was writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten for ſome particulars, &amp; lay at it
<pb facs="tcp:3223:6"/> vvere buried in forgetfulnes, by me, the ſame alſo being at the laſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed by ſome good breethren whome I much loue and reuerence in the lord, I was at the length ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come &amp; could not chooſe but yeild. Wherein though ſome perhaps may ſuppoſe that I labour, in publiſhing an vnneceſſarie &amp; impertinent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe theſe ignorant dayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Doctrine for building of men vp in knovvledge and iudgement, and theſe careleſſe and contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times, abounding vvith all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of looſnes and levvdnes, craue rebuke rather, and exhortation for care and conſcience in the dueties vve knovve, as a more fit and meete argument for this diſſolute age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet being aſſured of this, both by mine owne knovvledge, and other mens faithfull reportes, that ſundrie there are abroad in this land, and amongſt the reſt, euen ſome of you and yours, that as in regarde of your ſpirituall combats and bickerings, and the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:3223:6"/> aſſaultes and temptations you haue found therein, had need of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heauenly comfort, I could not but as in a generall care, for all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ones, to vvhome I wiſhe all the comforts of God, as to my ovvn ſoule: ſo in particular good vvil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes you your ſelues (vvhoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard comfort, and outvvard ioy, I vvould bee glad and ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure at all times, and by all meanes, if I could tel hovv, but acquaint you and them (ſpecially ſith it is one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall portion of the ſvveet Manna, that the lord hath prouided for you) vvith ſuch pleaſaunt and delightfull conſolations, &amp; that out of the word as God by his ſpirit hath vvrought in mee, for the peace of mine ovvne heart, and by me, though vnvvorthie euery way, communicated vnto ſom others. What root they may take or effects they may bring forth I knovv not. Sure I am of this, my earneſt praiers vnto God, as in regard of his religion and vvorſhip, and heartie
<pb facs="tcp:3223:7"/> purpoſe in my ſelfe, as in reſpect of Chriſtian good vvill, is, that all that mourne in our Sion, might reape ſome good by the ſame: vvhich if it cannot bee effected, either by meanes of my ſinne that medle ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or by reaſon that the ſvveet things publiſhed, cannot ſo ſeaſonablie or for lacke of oportunitie come to their knovvledge, or becauſe that through diffidence they fore-cloſe the vvaie and paſſage of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto themſelues, (in all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye of vvhich deſertes, I ſhall ſurelye mourne muche) yet my hope and heartes deſire is, that all of you (my good friendes) might receiue ſome vvorthie fruite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as vvell thoſe amongeſt you that haue not as yet taſted of thys bitter cuppe, (a matter that you muſt looke for, and make an account of, if euer you vvill feele hovve ſweete the Lord is indeed) vvhile you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue GOD ſitting you, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing you vvith the beſt armour of
<pb facs="tcp:3223:7"/> proofe that can bee, before the day of battaile dravve nigh: as thoſe that haue beene or are tried (that beeing the verie ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Gods children) God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your preſent diſtreſſes, prouiding for you, and reuealing vnto you, the preſent comfortes of his moſt faithfull vvorde, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible trueth, that ſo both the one ſort and the other, hauing the povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of your ovvne ſinnes, in the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes of his ſonne, if not vtterlie remooued and cleane taken avvay, yet verie much leſſened, and as it vvere beaten dovvne, you might not onelye the more earneſtlie, oppoſe your ſelues agaiſt ſatan in his ſleights and haue an aſſured hope of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ioyfull victorie, againſt him and his aſſaults, but alſo may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſtand, yea to ouercome in the day of euill, and to be more than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querors thorow him, that hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you &amp; waſhed you in his bloud, vvho I doubt not ſhall ſhortly and
<pb facs="tcp:3223:8"/> mightilie alſo tread him and all his forces whatſoeuer, down vnder your feet. Now the very god of peace ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctify you and al yours thorowout: &amp; I pray God, that your whole ſpirite and ſoule, and bodie, may bee kept blameles vntill the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: vvhereof I doubt not, becauſe he is faithful which hath called you, who alſo wil doe it. Good brethren pray for vs, that we may be readie in all things with vnfaigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to do the Lords vvill. At Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the tenth of of this December. 1589.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours readie and aſſured euer in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> T. W. <hi>the Lord his vnworthy ſeruant.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:8"/>
            <head>GRACE AND PEACE from God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe I haue not nowe a long time, eyther by wryting or by worde of mouth heard from you, (good Sir) I grow into ſome vncertain imaginations concerning your eſtate, (and by meanes thereof I freely confeſſe it) not onely into neglect of ſome duety towardes your ſelfe, (I meane comming to viſite you, and writing vnto you ſuch ſimple comfortes, as God hath bin pleaſed to explicate vnto me, which I call ſimple, not as of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, for ſo they are high and excellent, but as I haue them in my<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 4 7.</note> 
               <hi>earthen veſſell</hi>) but alſo into cold per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance at the leaſt, of ſom ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, (I meane my ſupplications and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3223:9"/> praiers vnto his maieſtie,<note place="margin">The duti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a Chriſtian and faithfull friend, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hys friend.</note> as on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. To pray for you, when God hath bene pleaſed to giue you, and in you me (for I take the fauours beſtowed vpon you, to be kindneſſe heaped vp vpon my ſelfe) thorow his merciful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance of you, a iuſt and holy occaſion to prayſe his name, ſhould be the ſinne of mine owne ſoule, becauſe it were the offring vp of a wrong ſacrifice, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vnto God a<note n="b" place="margin">Malac. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>blind beaſt</hi> (as it were) As on the other ſide, to ſtriue to yeeld you comfort, when you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a riche aboundance of the ſame from God himſelfe, thorowe his holie worde, and bleſſed ſpirite, were, as it might be thought to doe a needleſſe and vnneceſſarie worke, for where there is fulneſſe and plentie, ſcarſitie and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe will little appeare, and doe ſmall good. From the former, though I would gladly, as in regard of the lack of ſound knowledge touching your preſent condition, and in reſpect of the dulneſſe and heauineſſe of my ſoule, as to other good workes, ſo to that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlie,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3223:9"/> ceaſe till eyther from your ſelfe or others that are as your ſelfe, I ſhould be faithfully certified of the ſtate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are, that ſo I might, as a feeling member with you, eyther vnfeignedly<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 12.15.</note> 
               <hi>reioyce,</hi> in the aſſwaging of your tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and trials, or elſe heartily weepe, and pitie you, and pray with you, and for you, in the continuance and increaſe of theſe diſtreſſes: yet wil not the doubts that I haue in me touching the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of theſe calamities, and the dutie that I owe vnto you, as in that behalfe let me vtterly leaue off, but needes I muſt nowe and then, (according to my poore meaſure) preſent you before God, and that by name in my requeſtes and prayers (though poore and faynt) In the other ſurely, I cannot (God ayding me) but inlarge my ſelfe to my vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, yea beyond it (if I could tell how) becauſe I know it to be the Lordes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured trueth that I ſhall deliuer, and though not fit perhappes now for your ſelfe (by reaſon of your preſent comfort and ioy) yet heereafter i may bee, of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3223:10"/> more then neceſſary vſe for your ſelfe and others alſo, when theſe darke and glomie daies of aſſaultes ſhall againe take holde of you.</p>
            <p>In both which reſpectes, as I reſt perſwaded that my poore paynes ſhall not vtterly periſh, ſo cannot I but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly aſſure mine own heart, that both the one and the other, ſhall be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of you, who are woont much to make of euerie thing that commeth from me. In conſideration whereof, I will the more willingly aſſaie (God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting me) the performance of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I purpoſe, that is the yeelding of you ſome ſuch comfortes, as<note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>the God of all conſolation</hi> hath giuen vnto me, not onely for the ſtaie of mine owne conſcience, but to the ende alſo that I might acquaint others that are in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation with the ſame.</p>
            <p>The dealings of God with his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſaintes and ſeruantes (in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe eſpecially) are as we knowe, by the light of the world, and by experience in our ſelues, and examples of others,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3223:10"/> that haue gone before vs, or liue with vs, diuers and ſundry, he throwing vs downe, and lifting vs vp, and<note n="e" place="margin">pſal. 90.3.</note> 
               <hi>turning vs to deſtruction, and yet ſaying, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne you ſonnes of Adam:</hi> whoſe wayes as euerie maner of way, ſo in this reſpect eſpeciallie, are much more vnſearchable, and paſt finding out, than<note n="f" place="margin">pro. 30, 19</note> 
               <hi>is the way of an Eagle in the ayre, the waie of a ſerpent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtone, or the way of a ſhip,</hi> going with a right fore winde and full ſayle, <hi>in the midſt of the mayne ſea,</hi> till God be pleaſed in the multitude of his mercies, in ſome meaſure to diſcouer the ſame vnto hys ſeruantes.</p>
            <p>What God will doe with you (good ſir) after ſo manifold and long trials is vnknowne to me, becauſe neither I, nor any other haue<note n="g" place="margin">Rom, 11, 34</note> 
               <hi>bene of his councell,</hi> in ſuch ſecret and particular purpoſes, ſpeciallie concerning others, whatſoeuer we may feel touching our ſelues. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, I cannot otherwiſe thinke or be perſwaded, but that you haue bene, are, and ſo ſhal be for euer,<note n="h" place="margin">&amp; 9.23. Tokens to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure men to be the veſſels of mercie.</note> 
               <hi>a veſſell of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3223:11"/> mercy,</hi> wherein I am dayly more and more confirmed, not onely by the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian carrying of your ſelfe, in the dayes of your former and preſent troubles, you patiently bearing them, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly calling vppon God, for heauenly ſtrength to vndergoe, and ouercome, but euen by the verie afflictions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that you felt or feele, God by them ſetting (as it were) his own marke vpon you, the better to knowe you for one of his owne ſheepe and ſonnes, and ſo <hi>conforming you</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. &amp; 8.29</note> 
               <hi>vnto the image of his beſt beloued</hi> in his ſufferinges, that in the ſame you might haue a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pledge of glorification with him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Manifold and long afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a verie grieuous temptation.</note>Wherein though I acknowledge that it cannot be but verie greeuous, to be long held and much exerciſed, and the rather becauſe it is not one, but mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold aſſaultes and temptations, with which you are troubled on euerie ſide, yet doubt I not, but that the iſſue and end that God ſhall worke of all theſe,<note place="margin">An anſwere to it of the end.</note> ſhalbe exceeding good, not onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of<note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>a far moſt excellent weight
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3223:11"/> of eternal glory,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I know they pledge vp in you &amp; other of Gods children, but of the effects alſo that for the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they bring forth in you,<note place="margin">Of the effects.</note> as adding an edge vnto your prayers, which for the time, ſeemed to be colde or dead ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: leſſening, yea beating backe the force of many other temptations, which no doubt might ſtrongly aſſault, and mightily encounter with you: confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming you in vnfeigned affection, to the obedience of Gods good will (a worthy worke doubtleſſe, and a matter of no ſmall difficultie) filling you, and that for your ſelfe and others alſo, with the comfortes and conſolations which are from aboue,<note place="margin">Afflictions to the faithfull, not ſo much a cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, as to looke to themſelues, and to cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for ayd and ſtrength.</note> whiche hardly but by ſuch meanes wee taſte of, or attayne vnto, with ſundrie ſuch like.</p>
            <p>In my poore iudgement therefore, you may, yea you ought to be ſo farre off from beeing diſcomfited and caſt downe in this eſtate, wherein you are, that you haue rather iuſt occaſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you to<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>lift vp your handes which hang downe, and to ſtrengthen your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3223:12"/> weake knees,</hi> yea to raiſe vp your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied ſpirites, aſſuring your ſelfe that howſoeuer the Lord lead you along, in manifolde and manifeſt afflictions, and carry you (as it were) from one ſorrow to another, yea howſoeuer hee ſeeme to bring you to the pits bruicke, and make all the ſurges, and<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 42.7.</note> 
               <hi>waues of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,</hi> to riſe vp againſt you and mount ouer your head, that yet <hi>I will not</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 4 8.</note> 
               <hi>deſtitute you, nor</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>fayle you for euer,</hi> as well becauſe hee trieth you no otherwiſe,<note place="margin">Two reaſons.</note> nor exerciſeth you no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than he hath done thoſe that haue bene deare and precious in his owne eyes, as alſo becauſe he is both faithfull and powerfull to perfourme, both in heauen and in earthe, whatſoeuer hee hath promiſed to the ſonnes of men, much more to his owne ſeruauntes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two apt ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods loue towardes his children.</note>Wherein alſo no doubt he dealeth no otherwiſe with you, than earthly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes doe many times with their owne deare children, who to make them the more plainly ſee, and the more ſtrongly to be perſwaded of their fatherly loue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3223:12"/> towardes them, and manlike ſtrength for their deliuerance, bring their ſayd children to the fire ſide, that ſo they may feele more than a woonted heate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and learne to feare it withall.</p>
            <p>The like they practiſe towards them alſo in another element, namely in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not onely carrying them all along the edge, brimme, or bancke, of ſome pond or riuer, but nowe and then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſemblance, as if they would throw or thruſt them into the ſame. And yet wee knowe they loue them no whit the leſſe for all this: nay we are aſſured of this, the more nigh they are to daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whether it ariſe from the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ignoraunce of the children themſelues, or ſeeme to be layd vppon them from the very louing and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parentes, the more ſure and faſt hold they take of them. And ſhal not we be much more perſwaded, I wil not ſay of the like loue, but of farre<note n="p" place="margin">Eſay. 49.15.</note> 
               <hi>more exceeding loue in God,</hi> towards his ſonnes and daughters? with whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towardes his people, and power
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3223:13"/> for his childrens good, no affections, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might (I dare auouch this) not of any, but of all, not men alone, but fathers and mothers in the worlde, (though lincked neuer ſo ſtraitly vnto vs) is no maner of way matchable, nor ſo much as meete to be thought or ſpoken of with it, at the ſelfe ſame time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obiection, anſwered by example.</note>Your troubles in the ſoule, and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dangers that way, cannot ſeeme in any equall or vpright iudgment, to be more greeuous, or further paſt recouery, than<note n="q" place="margin">Ionas. 2.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ionas</hi> his were, when he was in the Whales belly: and yet <hi>the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that great fiſh, to deliuer him vp againe,</hi> whoſe abſolute autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie he coulde not withſtand, but as a man that hath his ſtomacke ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, vomited him out. And is <hi>Gods</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Eſay 59.1.</note> 
               <hi>hand ſtreitened now, or his power ſhortned?</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal 77.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>or his mercy abated,</hi> that he can not or will not performe as much for you? Or rather doth not God worke then moſte mightily and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully both when in mens eyes the way is ſtopped vp, not onely agaynſt a deed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3223:13"/> but againſt hope or hart to conceiue it? To what ende tend theſe comfortable promiſes, both of the olde and the new teſtament:<note n="t" place="margin">Iſay 42.16.</note> 
               <hi>I will bring the blinde by a waie that they knowe not, and lead them by pathes that they haue not knowne: I will make darkneſſe light before them, and crooked thinges ſtreight: theſe thinges will I doe vnto them, and not forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> and againe:<note n="v" place="margin">Math. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt you:</hi> but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme vs more and more,<note place="margin">A ſingular comfort farre beyond expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation.</note> in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſſe and certaintie of hys goodneſſe towardes vs, and to let vs vnderſtand, though there bee infinite barres and lets betweene him and vs, ſo that his mercy cannot ſeeme to haue anie paſſage vnto vs, that yet hee will breake them all to peeces, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe<note n="x" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> euerie high thing, that ſo we may plainly perceiue, and effectually &amp; comfortablie feele, the incomprehenſible treaſure of his fauour towardes vs?</p>
            <p>If this be not comfortable, I know not what is: in which poynt of ſpecial
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3223:14"/> conſolation,<note place="margin">The cauſe mouing to write more largely of this poynt.</note> I write nowe, both the more willingly and largely vnto you, becauſe I perceiue by your laſt (though long ſince ſent vnto me, vnto which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I then ſhaped a ſhort aunſwere, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing becauſe I heard not from you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that had ſatiſfied you) and by ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of ſundrie, that loue vs both in the Lord (to which, for the further ſtirring of me vp thereto, I adde the dayly thoughts and feares of mine own hart concerning your caſe) that you haue not onely bene terrible ſhaken for the time, but<note n="y" place="margin">and 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſore buffeted,</hi> and that not with ſome one meane temptation, but with many great and grieuous aſſaultes: the conſideration whereof raiſed vp ſuch a thicke miſt before your vnderſtanding, whileſt you dwelt too much, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the minding thereof, and in the beholding of your owne, both vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and weakeneſſe, that as the comfortable ſight of Gods grace and goodnes towards you in Ieſus Chriſt, ſeemed for the time to be vaniſhed from before you, yea altogether loſt, (ſo you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3223:14"/> thought) in your ſelfe, and would haue perſwaded others, that you were vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned and caſt away.</p>
            <p>But be not anie whit at all diſmaied,<note place="margin">A reaſon or meane to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this temtation.</note> with the violence and rage of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, but rather comfort your ſelfe, yea aſſure your ſelfe of this, that Sathan dealeth herein no otherwiſe with you,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude.</note> than a cruel and bloud-thirſtie captaine, beſieging aninuincible and irrepugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hold, who at the firſt beginneth tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately and coldly (as you would ſay) as well for the ſparing of his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and charge, as to gaine ſome little credite with thoſe that are beſet: but when he ſeeth that preuayleth not, hee dooth by little and little increaſe the fierceneſſe of his batterie, and the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of his aſſault: but not gayning that way neyther, he putteth it al at once vpon the laſt puſhe, wherein hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the foyle, hee is glad alſo to betake himſelfe to a ſhamefull flight. And what though the cannons roare, yea the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cannons thunder in ſuch ſorte, that they make heauen and earth to ſhake
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3223:15"/> (as it were) and would ſeeme to ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them altogether, yet in trueth they are nothing els but ſure pledges of the waſting and wearing of your aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries forces, and diſhonourable run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning awaie on the one ſide, and moſte comfortable meſſengers on the other ſide, of your happie and ioyfull deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance approching, and euen at the dores: which as it plainely appeareth by this,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude</note> that euen as a little before day breake, the darkeneſſe is greateſt, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes commeth moſte comfortable light, ſteppe by ſteppe, and degree by degree, the Sunne with his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and heate, chaſing away all thoſe thicke miſtes and ſtrong ſmelling fogs ſo may we be certainly aſſured of it, by the manifold examples of the word, and particularly of him that was poſſeſſed,<note n="z" place="margin">Mar. 9.25.26.</note> with <hi>a dumbe and deafe deuil,</hi> out of whome when our ſauiour <hi>charged him to come, and to enter no more into him, he cried and rent him ſore, and left him for dead,</hi> taking (as we ſay) his pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>worthes then vppon him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3223:15"/> becauſe he knewe, that as his time was but ſhort, ſo hee ſhould neuer after mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt or vexe him.</p>
            <p>For your ſinnes which you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of,<note place="margin">Accuſation of conſcience for the ſight and giltineſſe of ſinne.</note> I ſuppoſe verely that they are more in your owne iudgement, than in the ſight of all the worlde beſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom notwithſtanding your hard accuſing of your ſelf, you haue through Gods goodneſſe liued an vpright and vnblamable life, and that not onely in the teſtimonie of them that feare God, but in the witneſſe alſo of them that<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>are without,</hi> which ought notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the greatneſſe of your aſſault in your ſelfe, to yeeld you no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that in the viewe not onely of thoſe that can iudge rightly: (ſuch as Gods children are, who haue their eyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened by the knowledge of his trueth) you haue caried your ſelfe chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, and yet if you had failed, would <hi>in the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 10.12. 1. Pet. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>multitude of loue</hi> (according to their duetie) <hi>haue couered a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of tranſgreſsions,</hi> but in the iudgement of thoſe, that are led with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3223:16"/> prying and malicious eyes (who manie times obſerue in Gods ſeruantes, more than they ſhould,<note place="margin">Of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of a tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> or iuſtly can, and the rather for their profeſſion and troubles ſake) haue lead a harmeleſſe and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable conuerſation.</p>
            <p>But let vs graunt that your owne heart accuſeth you much. What then? Accuſation implieth not conuictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, much leſſe condemnation, ſpeciallie in ſuch a height as we imagine. And yet withall giue me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaue to councell you, not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it further then it bringeth the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of truth with it.<note place="margin">The wicked haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable feeling of their ſins.</note> This I am ſure you cannot be ignorant of, that as the wicked want with profite &amp; continuance that ſting of hart (with profit I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though they haue it, it doth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no good: and with continuance, becauſe it is but as a flaſhe of lightning in them, rayſed vp for their greater iudgement, as ſoone vaniſhing as it doth appeare) ſo the godly looking too much vppon themſelues,<note place="margin">The feeling of the godly.</note> and their ſinnes, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding both from ſight and ſenſe, the viewe and memorie of Gods mercies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3223:16"/> lay to hard and heauie burthens vppon their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>Me thinketh this rather woulde be ſtood vppon, that ſith euen from that, that woundeth them moſt, I meane the continuall charging and accuſing of themſelues, men that haue their minds inlightned from God, may reape ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar conſolations, they ſhould labour euen from thence to gather ſtrong comfortes vnto themſelues againſt their tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which they may doe by this holy conſideration, that the heart wounded with the dailie ſight and ſenſe of ſinne that is paſt, is puſhed forward there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſpeedy and vnfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (God to that end ſetting the ſame before them, that ſo in the lothſomneſſe thereof they might make haſte vnto him) which otherwiſe as in the want thereof, it could not ſo much as thinke vpon, much leſſe performe: is ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo againſt ſinne that is to come, becauſe hardly haue anie bene found to fall into that which they haue with vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and dayly iudgement miſliked, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3223:17"/> themſelues principally, and in others ſecondarily, the fear of the former, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to keepe a good watche ouer themſelues in the latter: and is prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in and by themſelues, tenderly to pitie &amp; earneſtly to pray for ſuch, whoſe ſtate that waie foorth, they knowe and feel by experience in themſelues, to be as lamentable and as much to be regarded as their owne. All which bringing with them the glory of God, their own bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and other mens good, that euen in the leaſt thinges, cannot but yeeld them comfort, that ſeriouſly thinke thereupon, vnleſſe they will deeme Gods honour light, or their owne comfort baſe, or the loue of the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thfull, and their welfare, a meane, yea a vilde thing.</p>
            <p>But we will put the caſe, that your ſinnes were as huge and as high, as your ſelfe take them to be: yea let vs imagine that they had ſpread the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, throughout both heauen and earth, and did reach from the one end of the world to the other, yet who can, will, or dare denie, but that as God himſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3223:17"/> ſo his mercies towardes vs in Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="c" place="margin">Co. 3.20. The mercy of God in this life chiefly appeareth in the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>ouer reacheth</hi> them euery way, and the rather ſith his meanes are no waie in this life more euidently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, than in the forgiueneſſe of the ſinnes of his ſeruantes? Concerning which trueth we may, and ought to be certainly perſwaded, not onely by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">A reaſon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Gods nature, which is infinite.</note> taken from the infinitneſſe of Gods owne nature, who beeing infinite him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe can haue nothing in him, but that which is infinite, and therefore his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie beeing in him, muſt alſo be infinite, with whom (howſoeuer) <hi>our ſins be in numerable,</hi> as in reſpect of our ſelues:<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>for who vnderſtandeth his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> or is able to account his tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? yet they are finite and certaine as in regard of himſelfe, that<note n="e" place="margin">&amp; 147.4.</note> 
               <hi>counteth the number of the ſtars, and calleth them all by their names:</hi> but alſo from the large and moſte faithfull promiſes,<note place="margin">Of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> that in euerie place almoſt of his word, for the vnderpropping of our weake fayth, hee hath plainly and plentifully propounded vnto vs: amongeſt which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3223:18"/> euen theſe moſt ſweete ſayinges, ſeeme not of the leaſt reckoning:<note n="f" place="margin">&amp; 103.12</note> 
               <hi>As farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath hee remoued our ſinnes from vs.</hi> Againe in another place:<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Though our ſinnes were as Crimſin, they ſhal be made white as Snow, though they were red as Skarlet, they ſhall be as wooll.</hi> And again:<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Where ſinne hath abounded, there grace hath more than abounded:</hi> with ſundrie ſuche like, with which I knowe you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, as hauing laid them vp in your heart, for the peace of the ſame, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing expreſſed them with your mouth for the teſtification of your ioy.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue laboured, neither vnſoundly, as in regard of Gods trueth propounded, nor vnprofitably, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of you afflicted, nor vndutifully, as inconſideration of my ſelfe trauailing, generally to deliuer generall comfortes againſt generall tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>Now it remaineth that I come, to applie particular conſolations, (as if it were) ſpeciall medicines and plaiſters,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3223:18"/> to thoſe peculiar offences &amp; griefes, that you ſaie are in your ſelfe, and it hath pleaſed you to acquaint me withall, to this end (as I take it verily) that of my poore ſtore, and penurie indeede, you might yet receiue ſome ſpirituall reliefe and comfort. What meaſure of mercie I haue receiued that way, hee that hath bene pleaſed freely to giue the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, beſt knoweth. Howbeit howe ſmall or great ſoeuer it be, this doth not a little incourage me to a liberall vſe of the ſame, that I knowe certainly I ſhall not decreaſe mine owne by that I beſtow vpon others, but rather increaſe the ſame much, it ſeruing me, (as the widdowes<note n="i" place="margin">2, King. 4, 2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>pitcher of oyle</hi> did in the dayes of Eliſha, being miraculouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed) not onely to inable me, in ſome ſort to pay my debts, though it be but fiue ſhillinges in the pound (as we ſaie) but the reſt being ſufficient, for my ſelfe and my children to liue vpon.</p>
            <p>But to thoſe thinges which you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt your ſelfe, and to that firſt which you firſt put downe.<note place="margin">Obiections anſwered.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3223:19"/>
            <p>You ſaie you are greatly troubled with manifold feares &amp; much doubting. I beleeue it to be true. And who would not be of that minde, if they conſidered you, but as a man? howe much more then, if they behold you as a godly man, in whom ſuch things are better ſeen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe naturall blindneſſe is ſomewhat remoued, and more felt, becauſe hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hart, and benummedneſſe is in ſome meaſure taken away? yea I am ſo farre of from thinking theſe thinges to be diſcomfortable to you (though as feare &amp; doubting are in you, I cannot approoue them, becauſe they are in vs tainted thorow the corruption of nature) that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame as I take it, you may reape and receiue ſingular conſolation, not onely in this reſpect, that they bring forth in you good and gracious effects, of hartie praier to almightie God, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full watching ouer your ſelfe, tender pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and compaſſion towards others &amp;c. and all theſe in a greater meaſure, than you feel &amp; wil confeſſe: (&amp; yet herein me thinketh you ſhould do wel to giue glory
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3223:19"/> to God, and according to grace receiued yeeld his children a notable portion of comfort) but whileſt you are herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints &amp; ſeruants of God who haue gone before you in the fleſh, &amp; in the faith, yea euen to Ieſus chriſt him ſelfe, the eternal ſonne of the eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Dauid was a<note n="k" place="margin">2. Sam. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>man according to Gods own hart,</hi> &amp; vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord had ſet his eie &amp; delight for much good: and yet who more afflicted this way the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he, he conceiuing of God, as of one that was in vtter diſpleaſure with him, and that had cleane forgotten him, and quite take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mercy from him? Of which if you doubt, may it pleaſe you to peruſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 6. &amp; 38. &amp; 42. &amp; 77. &amp; 88. &amp; 102.</note> 6.38.42.77.88.102. (whither alſo for ſhortnes ſake I do referre you) &amp; I doubt not but you ſhalbe thorowly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded therof.<note n="m" place="margin">Act. 9.15. &amp; 26.18.</note> Paul was <hi>an elect &amp; choſen veſſel,</hi> and that not onely to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Chriſts name among the gentiles,</hi> but euen vnto eternal life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.7</note> 
               <hi>leaſt he ſhould be exalted out of meaſure thorow the abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of reuelations, there was giuen vnto him a prick in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3223:20"/> the fleſhe, and the Angell Satan to buffet him:</hi> which leaſt we ſhould ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to be peculiar vnto him, he doth in another place affirme of him ſelfe and the faythfull together:<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 2.17. &amp; 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Though wee doubt, yet we deſpaire not.</hi> But what ſtand we repeating theſe petie examples (which though they be pregnant for the purpoſe whereunto they are produced, are not yet matchable with that that followeth) ſith we may moſt liuely ſee it in him, who (<hi>though hee was compaſſed about with our fleſhe,</hi> was yet free from the taint or ſtaine of anie corruption, and though he had na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall paſſions, was vtterly voyd of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie or ſinne in them, or any thing els whatſoeuer) being the very true and naturall ſonne of God, and equall with the father, was ſo farre humbled and brought lowe, that hee did yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding through fearefull feeling of Gods wrath, and extreme anguiſhe in himſelfe, demand of his father<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 27.46.</note> 
               <hi>whie hee had forſaken him?</hi> Of whome alſo the Apoſtle witneſſeth by the ſpirit,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3223:20"/> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>that in the daies of his fleſh, he did offer vp his prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with ſtrong crying, and teares vnto him, that was able to ſaue him from death, and was heard alſo in that which hee feared.</hi> Nowe if the ſtrength of temptations coulde bring our ſauiour to ſo lowe an eſtate, and hard condition, (as a man would ſaie) ſo that he ſeemed, not onely to be at the verie brinke, but to be plunged into the pit, not of feare alone, but of doubting and diſtruſtfulneſſe, (as it might ſeeme) who yet notwithſtanding was the onely beloued of God, and had receiued all the graces of the Spirite generallie, and therefore no doubt the ſpirite of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and power particularlie, in moſte abſolute and full meaſure: ſhall wee thinke it ſtrange that the ſonnes and daughters of God, (who during the time of their mortalitie vpon earth, haue ſinne dwelling in their brittle bodies: &amp; who alſo, howſoeuer they be beloued of God, are not affected for their owne ſakes, but for his ſake alone: and who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3223:21"/> notwithſtanding many gifts they haue receiued, for the gathering together and building vp of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues and of the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of ſaintes, haue yet not ſo much as a ſparke or crum of grace, compared with the infinite and incomprehenſible treaſures of Gods goodneſſe in Chriſt) be greatly aſſaulted, and daily beaten on euerie ſide, yea as ſeemeth vnto them ſelues and others, ſometimes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed? Neyther herein alone ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth your comfort (good ſir) yea our comfort, that we are<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>conformed and made like</hi> vnto the ſeruantes of God, yea, <hi>the only begotten ſonne of God, in his and their ſufferinges:</hi> but that as hee cauſed his almightie<note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrength to appeare</hi> in their poore weakeneſſe, making<note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13</note> 
               <hi>an iſſue out of their</hi> temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations for them, that they might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, that the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke mercie, fauour and ſtrength hee will ſhew vnto vs, and in vs, notwithſtanding our infirmities: becauſe that as <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Eſay. 59.1.</note> 
               <hi>Arme of God,</hi> is not (thorowe length of time, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of wonders anie maner of waie)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3223:21"/> ſhortned, ſo is the fatherly affection, that hee ſetteth vppon his children vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnchangeable. Whereof yet wee may be the better aſſured, becauſe hee hath performed theſe great workes, not onely in ſome of his excellent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, through his grace &amp; ſtrength alone, but in Ieſus Chriſt our heade and Captaine, whoſe victorie as in other reſpectes, ſo in this particularlie is in ſuch ſorte become ours, that we cannot chuſe, but in him become more<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8, 37</note> 
               <hi>than conquerours</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſayth.) For if his abſolute obedience, be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to take awaie our ſinnes, and the imputation of his righteouſnes, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inough, to make vs ſtand as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and innocent, in the preſence of our heauenly father, why ſhoulde not his vanquiſhing both <hi>of death, and</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Heb, 2, 14</note> 
               <hi>him that had the power of death, that is the deuill,</hi> be an aſſured pledge alſo of our ouercomming, ſith we know and beleeue that hee conquered not for hymſelfe but for vs, <hi>that wee in hym might bee,</hi> (as was euen nowe ſayd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3223:22"/> a little before) <hi>more than conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience or waywardnes.</note>The ſecond point that you complain of, as in regard of your ſelfe, is, the great impatience and waywardneſſe, that you finde at home, in your owne ſoule, the ſame ſometimes breaking out ſo farre, that it is not onely made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto God and men, thorow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet behauiour, and vnſauorie words, but manie times alſo breaketh forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to better curſinges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwere.</note>This I cannot chuſe bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be hard and heauie, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of your ſelfe, and the iniquitie high and great, as in reſpect of God. Howbeit euen againſt this alſo you ſhal well perceiue and finde,<note place="margin">A Comfort.</note> that the Lord hath prouided comfort for you, yea com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y worde: which word of his, as it farre exceedeth all humaine ſpeach and writing, that euer haue bin, are, or ſhalbe, and is indeede to ſpeake propeperly, the onely trueth: ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the comfortes therein conteined, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſurmount all worldly conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3223:22"/> whatſoeuer, and are indeede onelie to be taken for the true ioyes.</p>
            <p>In which reſpect I wou d haue you not to be afraid, for the magnifying of Gods ſingular mercies, and for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling of the comfortes of the word, to your ſpirituall ioy, to vrge and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as hard as you can, and as farre as anie maner of way you may with trueth, your owne ſinne, and yet I am ſure you ſhall neuer find it to reache further, than to blaſpheme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the father or the ſonne, to which depth of iniquitie for anie thing I know it hath not atteined. But ſuppoſe it had aſcended ſo high: doth not yet our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour (being trueth it ſelfe) in the word of all trueth aſſure vs,<note place="margin">2 Math. 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>that euerie ſinne and blaſphemy ſhalbe forgiuen vnto men,</hi> yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>blaſphemie againſt the ſonne of God?</hi> which yet that wee might be the better aſſured of,<note place="margin">Paule.</note> we haue a comfortable example in <hi>Paule,</hi> who confeſſeth of himſelfe againſt himſelfe, for the plaine proofe of the trueth of this point, that ouer and beſides that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3223:23"/> he <hi>was</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 1 13.</note> 
               <hi>a perſecutor,</hi> he <hi>was a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer,</hi> and yet found fauour with the Lord to obteine forgiueneſſe. To which particular example, tending doubtleſſe to no ſmall comfort of conſcience, you may adde, for the further not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging, but ſtrengthning of your own ioy, that the ſinnes that you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or the blaſphemie that you haue ſpoken, haue not bene done or ſayd with a high hand, or of prepenſed malice, but rather of infirmitie (though happily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt knowledge) and the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a paſſionate and troubled ſpirite, rather than of any wilfulneſſe, which weakeneſſe in you Satan by Gods appointment hauing you vppon the racke (not to fetche anie thing from you againſt your ſelfe, but to make your patience, conſtancie and faith, playnly known to others, effectually felt in your ſelfe, and graciouſly accepted in hys owne eyes) hath vſed as a meane, more and more to trouble your heart, but yet not to ouerthrowe your hope. And euen this conſideration of the maner of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3223:23"/> haue Gods ſaintes obſerued in themſelues, not ſo much to leſſen their tranſgreſſions (for they knowe that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſinne in it owne nature<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> deſerueth death) but to comfort their conſciences in the dayes of their diſtreſſe, without which indeede, they can hardlie ſerue God religiouſlie, or faythfullie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge anie duetie either publike or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate. And this to be true, we may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt others behold it in Paule, who ſayth of hymſelfe in the height and depth of his grieuous iniquities,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>that hee was receiued to mercie: for that hee did it ignorantly thorow vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</hi> And if this aforded hym com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, I ſee no reaſon why it ſhoulde not yeeld you conſolation, ſpeciallie ſith your ſinnes, (for anie thing wee knowe) are much leſſe than his, and you haue to deale with the ſelfe ſame God, who is nowe, as then,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 103 8. Exod 34.6</note> 
               <hi>ſlowe to vvrath, and of great compaſsion, paſsing by ſins, and forgiuing iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and reſtoring mercie vnto thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of generations.</hi> Neyther is that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3223:24"/> of leſſe force in my minde,<note place="margin">An other te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie to comfort.</note> to leſſen your ſinne and to increaſe your comfort, that either before the offence committed, or in the deede doing, or after it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, you had a ſpirite within you, that did not onely tell you it was euill, but checked you and controlled you, in &amp; about the action it ſelfe: wherunto alſo though you were drawen, and did for the time ſleepe, and delight therein, yet would it not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue you reſt, till ſuche time as it had cauſed you, vnfeignedlie to hate it, humbly to confeſſe it, and in a notable meaſure of<note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> godly ſorrow, ſoundly to repent you of the ſame, which thing as the wicked doubtleſſe,<note place="margin">The wicked hate not their ſinnes.</note> ſeldome (or not at all) atteine vnto, for they notwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hſtanding the vglineſſe of ſinne loue it,<note place="margin">A ſpeciall grace to gods children to hate their ſinnes.</note> and hide their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons continuallie: ſo are they ſpecial gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, beſtowed vpon ſuch penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as God is pleaſed, thorowe hys mercy in Chriſt, to call vnto himſelfe: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch as it may appeare by many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examples of the holy ſcripture, ſo ſeemeth it to me to be iuſtificable, by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3223:24"/> theſe words of the Apoſtle.<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 5. i7.</note> 
               <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirite, and the ſpirite againſt the fleſh, ſo that you cannot doe the ſame thinges you would.</hi> And in another place,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>what I woulde that doe I not but what I hate, that doe I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pull vp your heart therefore (I pray you) and be of good comfort,<note place="margin">An exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h that from the ſinnes that you haue co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſpeciallie in the maner of the doing of them, and from your ſelfe ſpeciallie in the wreſtling aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in your ſelfe againſt ſinne, God and his word would haue you to reape comfort and conſolation.</p>
            <p>And as for your part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lar caſe of a troublous heart, and diſq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>t ſpirite, what is it els I pray you, but euen that that hath taken holde of Gods ſaintes, as well as of you? doth not Iere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ah himſelfe curſe (as it were) himſelfe, and the mother that bare him, and brought him into the worlde, when hee ſaith:<note n="e" place="margin">Iere. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>Woe is me, my mother that thou haſt born me a man of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3223:25"/> to all this land:</hi> And doth not Ionah, when God debated with him about the withering of the gourd, that God prepared to be a ſhadowe ouer his head, and to ſhelter him from heate, and demaunded of him,<note n="f" place="margin">Iona. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>whether hee did well to be angrie for the gourd,</hi> did not hee (I ſaie) aunſwere and ſay <hi>I doe well to be angrie vnto death?</hi> And yet theſe were excellent men and worthie prophetes, and ſuch as had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued rare grace from God: no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile then though men of leſſe ſauour fall more? But moſte plainelie ſhall you ſee this in Iob, of whome I pray you giue me leaue to write largely for your good. Hee opened his mouth ſo wide, that he bitterly <hi>curſed the night wherin he was conceiued,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iob. 3.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the day wherin he was borne:</hi> yea, he thundred out execrations againſt many excellent creatures of God, which could not bee but blaſphemie againſt the Creator himſelfe, whoſe glorye is not onely much ioyned with, but greatlie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the woorke of his owne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3223:25"/> handes, as wee may perceiue by this that Salomon ſaieth:<note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 17. &amp; 14.31.</note> 
               <hi>hee that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the poore</hi> (or as it is in an other place) <hi>mocketh him, reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth or reprocheth him that made him.</hi> Yea if wee reade hys Booke with iudgement, wee ſhall ſee that hee doeth not onelie thus indirectlie (as a man woulde ſay) in his wordes, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe againſt God, while he hudleth out heapes of curſes againſt his workes, but proceedeth ſo farre, that hee ſeemed not eyther affrayde or aſhamed, to take God (euen God himſelfe) by the face, and to accuſe him, (though moſt faſlie) of iniuſtice, as maie euidentlie appeare, as well by Iobes owne woordes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, in many places of his ſayde booke, as by the Lordes owne voice and anſweare, out of the whyrlewinde, Chapter<note n="i" place="margin">Iob. 38. &amp; 39.</note> 38.39. And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, this man found fauour with the Lord, not onely to bee reſtored to a farre better eſtate in worldly reſpectes than before hee hadde, but alſo to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3223:26"/> haue the iniquitie of his hart and mouth freely pardoned, yea hee himſelfe, and that by the holie Ghoſt himſelfe, to be made a worthie paterne and example, to all ages to come, as of manie ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, ſo particularly of patience, which you ſay you lacke: for proofe whereof remember what Saint Iames ſaith of him:<note n="k" place="margin">Iame. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>yee haue heard of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Iob, and haue knowne what ende the Lord made: for the Lord is verie pitifull and mercifull.</hi> Where marke I pray you, that hee notwithſtanding all his frowardneſſe againſt his friends, who came (no doubt with a minde) to viſit and comfort him howſoeuer, either thorowe his own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or their euill, he was prouoked to ſaie,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>miſerable comforts are you, all the ſorte of you:</hi> notwithſtanding his horrible execration of the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of god, which neuer did him hurt, but manie wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s tended to profite, and pleaſure h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, for eaſe, comfort, health, and ſtrength: notwithſtanding all his inward impatience and fretting againſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3223:26"/> God, and outward furie, and open char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of him, to doe him iniurie and wrong, is yet ſet before vs as a worthie paterne of patience, and a mirror of a milde and quiet ſpirite.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges perhaps maie ſeeme ſtraunge to you, and you in your imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation may ſuppoſe, that they can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree well together.<note place="margin">The worke of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if you will labour wiſely to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne the worke of reformation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation that God hath in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the remaynders of their owne corruption, that beeing alwaies good and excellent in it ſelfe, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s naught and abhominable, yea manie times alſo much darkenening the other: and conſider that notwithſtanding our ſinnes, God is mercifully pleaſed in Ieſus Chriſt, to cure and to couer them all, and to receiue vs vnto himſelfe in him, not onely as though we had neuer ſinned, but as if wee had actually and really fulfilled all righteouſneſſe: and haue receiued thorow the holie miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the worde, and the gracious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3223:27"/> of of the ſpirite, the eie of faith to ſee, and the hand of faith to lay holde of, and to apply this particularlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your owne ſelfe, in the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wherein you are, you ſhall eaſilie knowe in your vnderſtanding, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie feele in your ſoule, ſtedfaſtlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in your heart, and francklie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with your mouth this woorthie difference, and moſt comfortable point, wherein alſo for the better inſtruction, or perſwaſion of you, or both, I will (by your good patience) ſpend a line or two.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of ioy and feare in one perſon, and at one time.</note>Ioy and feare doubtleſſe, in humaine iudgement ſeeme one of them to be ſet againſt another: and yet in the holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, it is reported of the women, which went to ſee Chriſtes ſepulchre, that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the glorious apparition of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell at that place, and the declaration of Chriſtes reſurrection,<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 28.8.</note> 
               <hi>they departed quickly from the ſepulchre, with fear and great ioy:</hi> feare as I take it, at the ſtrangeneſſe of the ſight, and much ioy, for the comfortable and gladſome tidinges that they had heard. And what
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3223:27"/> I pray you is indeede more contrarie one vnto another, than beliefe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe?<note place="margin">The like of beliefe, and vnbeliefe.</note> And yet the father of the ſicke childe in the Goſpell, hauing receiued this comfortable ſpeache from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour himſelfe,<note n="n" place="margin">Marke. 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>that all thinges are poſsible vnto him that beleeueth, cryed out with teares,</hi> and that when he prayed, <hi>Lorde I beleeue, helpe my vnbeliefe,</hi> calling and counting, that beginning of fayth, that God had wrought in him beliefe, and the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and diſtruſt of hys owne hart, vnbeliefe. And if it haue beene ſo in hym and others, and wee ſtedfaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y beleeue the ſame, becauſe wee ſee it is reuealed vnto vs in the written worde of God, why ſhoulde wee not perſwade our ſelues, that the lyke is, and may bee in vs, becauſe Gods workes are this waie, nowe as then, all alike.</p>
            <p>But wee are hyndered from the comfortable ſight, and the ioyfull fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heereof, one while by ſuffering of oure myndes to bee whollie taken
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3223:28"/> vp, with the beholding of our owne ſinnes onely, forgetting in the meane while the graces and fauours, that God hath bene pleaſed freely to beſtow vpon vs, for his glorie and our good: and an other while by imagining, that whileſt we haue not perfection of mercie and goodneſſe, here we haue receiued no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable meaſure of grace and loue: the former of theſe be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing dangerous, vtterly to ouerwhelme vs with diſtruſt, and the latter preſt and readie to cauſe vs to deface Gods mercies in vs, but both of them powerfull, to deteyne and withhold vs, from yeelding due glorie to God, whileſt which way ſoeuer wee looke, wee thinke we haue nothing (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yet receiued ſomething) &amp; ſo yeeld him not holie praiſe and thankes,<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal 50.14.23. &amp; 69.32. &amp; 11.16.12.13.</note> the beſt and onely ſacrifice, that he requireth at our handes for all his fauours.</p>
            <p>As for that which ſeemeth heerein moſt to wound you, namely, your blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt God (as you call it) or ſpeaking euill of him, I woulde pray you, ouer and beſides that that hath bin
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3223:28"/> ſaid alreadie, to weigh this following, and ſee whether it may not ſatiſfie you, concerning that great doubt, yea or no.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Put the caſe that ſome one, that had borne you ſingular good will, not onely for worldly conſiderations, but in the trueth alſo: and as a ſound teſtimonie thereof, had euerie where as occaſion had bene offered, giuen you a due and iuſt commendation, for the good partes that be in you: and yet afterwardes puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp in a haughtie imagination of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s owne heart, or forgetting your great fauours ſhewed him, or his own former friendſhip profeſſed and practiſed, or miſlead by ſome lewd and hypocriticall companie, (as al and euerie one of theſe thinges, are ſtrong and mightie (no doubt) to carrie men awaie) ſhould ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelfe, or together with them in companie, either thinke or ſpeake euill of you: Tell me I pray you howe you would behaue your ſelfe towardes ſuch a one, ſpeciallie if hee ſhould vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly confeſſe his offence, and proteſt ſincere ſorrowfulneſſe of heart for his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3223:29"/> ſinne? ſurely I doubt not but the<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> loue of God ſhedde abroad into your heart, would make you ready &amp; willing, with a ſound affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to forget and to forgiue and to reciue him euen as though he had not fallen. And ſhal or can you, (which in reſpect of Gods infinite fauor towardes you, haue not ſo much as a crum of loue towardes men) ſhewe yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſuch a larges of the ſame? and god<note n="q" place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>who is loue it ſelfe</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) be ſkant and pinching, as in this reſpect? for mine own part, rather than I would thinke or ſay ſo, I would hold and affirme, that the bottomleſſe depths of the huge and great Ocean, might be dried vp &amp; want water, before the ponds and the ceſternes, that in a parched land men haue digged vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or anie thing that is more abſurd &amp; vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than this, if anie ſuch can be found.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doubting of his election to eternal life.</note>The laſt but yet that not of the leaſt importance, wherewith your heart is troubled, is that you cannot feele your ſelfe to be one of thoſe, whome God hath marked out to eternall life.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3223:29"/>
            <p>Wherein I would firſt haue you to know, and perſwade your heart of this, that as the miſeries of the reprobate,<note place="margin">The repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate cannot truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, much leſſe feele their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</note> and their condemnation alſo, is more, I will not ſay than is well felt, for feeling they haue little or none, but well concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their harts not beeing fit to thinke either of their ſinne, or iudgement due vnto them for the ſame: ſo many times the fauour of God is certaynly muche more, towardes and in his ſeruantes, than eyther they themſelues, or others for them can well perceiue. For as it is moſt true, that naturall blindneſſe, and benummedneſſe of heart, with a ſenſual delight the wicked take in ſinne, purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all maner of iniquitie with pleaſure, wil not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſee their damnable eſtate, at the leaſt wiſe to dwell vpon the contemplation of it with fruite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thorowe impenitencie of heart, they bee<note n="r" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.26.</note> held captiues of Satan at his pleaſure: ſo it is as certaine, that by reaſon of the remaynders of a darke minde, which reſteth euen in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as yet) in parte, vnreformed, they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3223:30"/> be ſometimes as farre off from concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpirituall fauours from God. And no marueile, becauſe beeing ſpirituall things, they muſt be<note n="s" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14</note> ſpiritually diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and we knowe, that as other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo that of a diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing ſpirite, is not onely in vs in part, but ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e times ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be quenched in vs, and hidden from others thorowe the aſhes of our corruption. And what reaſon can be ſhewed to the contrarie, but that if want of ſight and feeling in the wicked can for the time (though not for euer) put out feare and pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, and all ſenſe of the ſame: but alſo that the reliques of ſinne in the righteous, and the ſight they haue of it, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare and griefe of heart that they conceiue for it, ſhould for the time, though not alwaies, bleare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, the hope and the ioy, that God would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them to conceiue, Satan al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> working no doubt in all theſe temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations of the wicked, and the godly, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o he might (if he coulde t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l how) preuaile vpon all, both good and bad.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3223:30"/>
            <p>By which you may well perceiue, that in this moſt high,<note place="margin">What the godly in ſuch a caſe, ought to doe.</note> yet moſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable point, you are to goe beyond your owne reache and feeling yea to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from your ſelfe: (who by reaſon, ſometimes of blindneſſe, and ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etimes of partialitie, are vnfit to bee a iudge in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s cauſe) that ſo being ſpoiled o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truſt and donfidence in your ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the<note n="t" place="margin">Iere. 17.5</note> arme of fleſh and bloud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls where you may repaire vnto him, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> alone is the God of all ſtrength, both ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ward and inward, and who will indeede for you and all his, effect that, which ſhalbe moſt meete for his glorie, and your eternall comforts.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſecond thing that I would pray you well to weigh, namely, that as according to the trueth of the holie ſcriptures, God hath pleaſed, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the infinite mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tude of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, in Ieſus Chriſt, to elect you to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e euerlaſting,<note n="t" place="margin">Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 1 4</note> before the founda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions of the world were laid: ſo hath he in time plainly manifeſted vnto you, and by you vnto others, that his great grace of your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3223:31"/> eternall etettion, firſt in vouchſafing you, (though vnworthie of your ſelfe, yet for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake) thorowe the miniſterie of his holy worde, and by the powerfull working of his bleſſed ſpirite, an effectual calling, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 13.48. &amp; 16.14.</note> no ſooner ſpake vnto you, but withal pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your eares, and boared your heart to vnderſtand and beleeue, he working in you alſo this readineſſe, with vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned affection to ſaie,<note n="v" place="margin">1. Sam 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake Lord for thy ſeruant heareth:</hi> God dealing with you heerein for your ſoule,<note place="margin">The ſpirituall meanes of Gods mercie.</note> as hee hath done alwaies with you for your body, that is beſtowing vppon you, the ſpirituall meanes of his mercie, and making them mightie in you, to worke his will, not vnto iudgement, as in the wicked, but to eternall ſaluation, as in his ſaintes and ſeruantes. And this I take to be that, which the Apoſtle ſaith. Roman. 8.<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> 
               <hi>Whom he predeſtinate, them alſo he called.</hi> Secondly by giuing you care and conſcience, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne theſe excellent graces, of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall election from before all times, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3223:31"/> effectuall vocation in time, with the fruites of faith, and the deedes of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed obedience, and that both in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices of pietie towards his maieſtie,<note place="margin">The duties of pietie.</note> you hauing a minde to be often and earneſt with him in prayer and thankeſgiuing, adioyning thereto for your better direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein, dayly reading of the word, deepe meditation, and chriſtian confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference therein: and alſo in the duties of charitie towardes men,<note place="margin">Of charitie.</note> you not onely not deteming from anie, that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto them, but rendring vnto euerie one that which is right &amp; equall, and ſpecially hauing care of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſaints,<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 12.15</note> 
               <hi>vveeping there with them that weep, and reioycing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that teioyce.</hi> And this is that that the Apoſtle ſaith in another place, that<note n="z" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4</note> 
               <hi>God hath choſen vs in Chriſt, that we ſhould be holy &amp; without blame before him in loue.</hi> And againe:<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The ſtrong foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God remaineth ſure, &amp; hath this ſeal, the lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his: &amp; let euery one that calleth on the name of Chriſt depart
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3223:32"/> from iniquitie.</hi> In which reſpect alſo it is, that Peter admoniſheth vs,<note n="b" place="margin">peter. 1.10. Why theſe duties are propounded to vs in the word.</note> 
               <hi>to giue diligence to make our calling and election ſure, by good vvorkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that eyther the one or the other, either as in reſpect of God, are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>for his giftes and calling are ſuch, as he repent him not thereof:</hi> are vnſure, as in regard of our ſelues, becauſe we haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thorow his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs (though not that that wee ſhould, yet) a minde bowable and ready to harken vnto, to loue and obey the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly voyce and calling of our gracious God. But therefore are theſe thinges propounded vnto vs in the word, on the one ſide to ſtop the mouthes of careleſſe blaſphemers, who in the vaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their owne heartes, feare not to affirme, that if they he elected, they may liue as they liſt: and on the other ſide to lift vp the weakned ſpirites of many of Gods deare ſeruantes, who finding ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the faith of their election, or the fruites following the ſame, fewe and ſkant in them, beginne to call their elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3223:32"/> into queſtion: wherein ouer and beſides the diſcomfortes and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragementes, that cauſeleſly they caſt vpon themſelues, they doe great iniurie to God, whileſt they make him that is certaine in his purpoſes and acts, to be<note n="d" place="margin">Num. 23.29. Iſa. 51.8. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. 1.17.</note> as wauering as mutable man, and then to be ſubiect to alteration &amp; change when they ideſſie fantaſie or imagine the ſame. Yea they ſpeake contrarie to common ſenſe and reaſon: for if the ſins that are from our ſelues, may (as they ought indeede) iuſtly caſt vs down, ſhall not the graces that are in vs from god, be much more mightie to raiſe vs vp? What, is God become leſſe than man? or are his mercies inferiour to mans tranſgreſſions?</p>
            <p>But we will put the caſe that we fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in thoſe good workes, that that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath bin put downe, &amp; that out of the very word of trueth, concerning the fruites of our faith were falſe: yet ſee, what euen in ſuch a caſe alſo, if it wer ſo, the holy Ghoſt ſaith, for our full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion and reſolute comfort: <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>It is not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3223:33"/> in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The whole worke of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on Gods mercie in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>but in God, that ſheweth mercy,</hi> that ſo the whole worke of our ſaluation, and euerie part and peece of it bee aſcribed onely and wholie, to his free fauour towardes vs in Ieſus Chriſt. For as this is ſure, that God ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not vs for our good workes, be they neuer ſo manie or excellent, becauſe hee ſhall haue alwaies ſome thing for matter, or maner or ende and all, to ſaie againſt them, and vs for their ſakes, and to holde that, were indeede to eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Gods free mercie, and to anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate Chriſtes ſufferings, and to puffe vp fleſhe and bloud beyond all meaſure and trueth: ſo he will not condemne vs (vs I ſaie, and not men) becauſe of our eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll woorkes, though they be neuer ſo manie and grieuous (alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided that no man abuſe this doctrine of trueth and comforte, to licenciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and carnalitie, nor extend it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the perſons of whome we meane it: namely the elect and faithfull, who as they haue receiued this ſweete pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3223:33"/> from God,<note n="f" place="margin">&amp; 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that to them that are in Chriſt there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo they haue this giuen vnto them <hi>that they walke not after the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhe, but after the ſpirite)</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 33.19. Rom 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>For hee will haue mercie on him, to whome he will ſhewe mercie, and he wil haue compaſsion on him, on whome h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will ſhewe compaſsion.</hi> And this is it that the Lorde hym ſelfe ſayth in Eſaiah:<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 43 25.</note> 
               <hi>I euen I am hee that putteth awaie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir iniquities for myne owne ſake, and will not remember theyr ſinnes.</hi> And in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah, eſtabliſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were) a newe contract with hys Seruauntes, hee make Ieſus a principall part of the couenaunt:<note n="i" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. 31.34. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>That hee will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue all theyr iniquities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theyr ſinnes no more:</hi> or as it is al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eadged by the holie Ghoſt in the eight Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Hebrues, <hi>I will be mercifull to theyr vnrighteouſneſſe, and I will remember their ſinnes, and their iniquities no more,</hi> vſing all theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3223:34"/> wordes, of vnrighteouſneſſe, ſinnes, iniquities, &amp;c. to aſſure vs, that neyther the heynouſneſſe, nor the multitude of our tranſgreſſions, ſhall for euer ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate betweene the Lord &amp; vs, but that of his infinite mercie, he will receiue vs, &amp; though we had not offended.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note>Of which wee may be the better aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by this, that if we would giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vnto the worde of an earthly man, ſpeciallie if wee had ſome experience of his fidelitie, and that in matter of grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> importance (and yet we know me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be but men, that is fraile &amp; inconſtant) we ſhould much more beleeue the trueth of the eternal our God (confirmed vnto vs by the deathe and bloudſheding of hys ſonne, the beſt pledge of immutabil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that can be, and that in cauſes of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt weight concerning vs) who alwais<note n="k" place="margin">Mala 3.6.</note> remaineth like vnto himſelfe, and who rather than he will fayle vs in hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or falter with vs in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ſame, giuing vs leſſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee hath ſaid, will inlarge himſelfe, (I cannot ſaie, beyond his word and trueth,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3223:34"/> for that remaineth alwaies as large as himſelfe, and God the God of trueth ſhall neuer bee found a lier) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our heart and hope I am ſure.</p>
            <p>And ſurely for your ſelfe, in my mind this is one point that much perſwadeth me, and may yeeld you comfort, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can be vtterly taken awaie (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it may for the time be ſomewhat leſſened, that you belong vnto the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, &amp; are (as it were)<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa 49.16.</note> grauen vpon the palme of his right hand, that you haue not onely patiently ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (which is a rare vertue) but migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely vanquiſhed and ſubdued (which is a greater grace doubtleſſe) in him that is the God of your ſtrength, many and the ſame long and bitter temptations, which had you not belonged to God, and hee himſelfe had not reſerued you for daies and times not onely of comfort in this life: but of eternall ioy, you coulde not haue indured, much leſſe ouercome: for as this is a certaine trueth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal 34.19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>manie are the miſeries of the righteous, but the Lord deliuereth him out of all,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3223:35"/> and that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s children are conquerours ouer many aſſaults, by the ſtrength and power that they haue receiued from<note n="n" place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6 33. Rom 8.37.</note> him: lo our onely temptation, and the ſame as ſhort and ſmall as may be, is able to quaile the ſtrongeſt Gia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reprobate and to throw him downe headlong, into the bottomleſſe pit of hell, as experience of the wicked (who in this reſpect to withſtand, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t weaker then wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er) and ſundrie parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular examples of former ages, and of our preſent time, doe playnely p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, if I thought it conuenient to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge them.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee my minde, and poore iudgement, concerning your ſcruples, in ſuch meaſure and maner deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red, as God hath inabled me. Where alſo I muſt confeſſe I woulde gladly end, as beeing almoſt wearie in my ſelfe, and tedious (I feare me) vnto you, ſauing that the dutie of holie loue that I beare you, will not ſuffer mee to let ſlippe a nece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſarie admonition, that euen nowe commeth to minde, and ſauing alſo,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3223:35"/> that your preſent diſtreſſed eſtate (as I feare) calleth for the inlarging of my ſelfe, ſo farre as I may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe ſome more particular courſe of comforte, than as yet I haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            <p>Touching the former of theſe two,<note place="margin">An admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> let mee intreate you, (I beſeeche you) as the trueth is, not to imagine as I knowe ſome doe, that there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes like effectes and fruites of Gods grace in the heartes, and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hys people, I meane eyther as in regard of feeling, or action, for wee knowe by that, that we haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in others, and obſerued in our ſelues (if euer God gaue vs grace to marke the one, or the other) that there is euerie day, yea almoſt euery houre in a daye, an entercourſe of the ſame, God by hys ſpirite manie tymes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to good thinges, and ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the ſtrength thereof, our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: and ſometymes agayne the power of oure iniquitie, preuayling, and alwayes getting the vpper hand,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3223:36"/> the Lord (no doubt) thereby prouiding, for hys glorye, whileſt wee attribute all the praiſe of our well doing vnto him, (to whome indeede alone all praiſe and honour belongeth) and for our good and that in a double reſpect, not onely whileſt by this meanes wee are made humble and lowly, before him and men, and in our owne eyes eſpeciallie, hauing ſpeciall recourſe vnto him by praier, for heauenly ſtrength, and comming to our brethren, for ſuch ſpirituall ayd, as they haue receiued from him: but alſo whileſt we learne, on the one ſide to loth that which is from our ſelues, as corrupt and defiled, and on the other ſide to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and foſter that which is from him, as good and pure, according to that rule of the Apoſtle,<note n="o" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19 20.</note> 
               <hi>Quench not the ſpirits, deſpiſe not propheſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſimilitude.</note>The Sunne it ſelfe a verie glorious creature, is not, no not in the ſummer time, alwaies alike hote and bright, but ſometimes is couered with cloudes, that keepe backe the brightneſſe, &amp; hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heate of the ſame from vs. The
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3223:36"/> like may we ſaie of another celeſtial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the moone it ſelf,<note place="margin">An other.</note> which ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinarie eclipſes that it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, ſomtimes aſcendeth higher, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times commeth ſower, &amp; is many times in the winter ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Others.</note> eſpecially kept from vs, by thicke miſts and darke fogs. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neede we for this to looke ſo high, for from terreſtriall or earthly bodies may we perceiue the ſame. The trees in the fields, and the plants and hearbs in the gardens, all winter long not onely want any good fruite, but ſeeme not ſo muche as to haue a leafe on them, yea the verie truncke and ſtocke it ſelfe maketh ſhewe in mans eyes to be dead, and to lacke that life, that we call vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue. And yet there is a ſappe or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall moyſture, that lyeth hid in the root, which when it is refreſhed with the heate of the ſinne, and comforted as it were, with the dewe that falleth from heauen, will yet notwithſtanding in due time proue vnto vs, that the tree, plant, or herbe, was neuer dead whatſoeuer we ſuppoſed. But what neede we to go
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3223:37"/> out of our ſelues, and from our own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to viewe this matter? we haue as plaine a demonſtration as may be. Our bodies to daie freſh and luſtie, and to morrowe wythered and dried vp,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 118.83.</note> 
               <hi>as a skinne bottle that hangeth in the ſmoke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Another.</note> and yet in time raiſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to haue naturall moiſture, and to performe with ſtrength and agilitie, as woorthy deedes as before.</p>
            <p>And euen ſuch doubtleſſe for a while is the ſtate of the children of God,<note place="margin">The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes.</note> who thorow the heynous offences that they haue committed, &amp; the ſtrength of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that they doe indure (ſpeecially when they are preſſed vpon them by the ſting of their own heart, or Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice) and wherein oftentimes thorow the power of naturall corruption, they lie ſleeping &amp; ſnorting (as it were) a great while, appeare vnto men (yea very many thinke and ſaie ſo of themſelues) as perſons forſaken of God, and remedie leſſe in this life, and paſt hope of recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for that which is to come. It is true that ſuch mens caſes are (for the time)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3223:37"/> ſpecially before men &amp; in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, hard and heauie. And if wee ſhoulde ſay or thinke otherwiſe, wee ſhoulde contradict Gods truth, which telleth vs <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>no afflictions</hi> (much leſſe this great one) <hi>is for the preſent ioious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but grieuous ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and ſtand vp againſt common ſenſe and reaſon, which plainly prooueth to our faces their condition to be pitifull.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, it is not as they affirme, deſperate and vnrecouerable, but rather thought not as in reſpect of it ſelfe yet as in regard of the conſolations that God intermingl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th with it, and the good fruites that he bringeth foorth by it, very comfortable.</p>
            <p>And therefore how ought you,<note place="margin">A conſolation</note> &amp; ſuch as you are to be raiſed vp (I come now to the ſecond point, namely conſolation) vpon whome the Lorde himſelfe hath ſette ſuch infallible notes of your adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and election vnto eternall life in Ieſus Chriſt? that no cloude that the enemie hath interpoſed betwixt you and God, or no myſt that in imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you haue rayſed vp in your ſelfe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3223:38"/> to ſtoppe the comfortable Sunne-ſhine of Gods fauour vnto you, nor no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame froſt or colde of winter, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it bee harde or ſharpe for the tyme, and ſenſibly felt of you, can kill the ſeed that is ſowen in your heart, by Gods word and ſpirite, or diſanull the<note n="r" place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.27.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting,<note n="s" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30</note> wherewith you are ſealed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of Chriſt: ſo louing, ſo faithfull and powerfull is God, in and for his Saintes, and that not onelie when they are aſſaulted with forraigne forces, but when they are aſſayed from within, and haue (as a man would ſay) the motions of their owne minde, and the imaginations of their owne hearts and heades, not only to conſpire aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt them, but euen to betraie them into the handes of their moſt cruell and deadlie enemies.<note place="margin">Obiections anſwered.</note> Howbeit, it may bee that you will ſaie, your ſelfe thinketh otherwiſe of of your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But be not your owne iudge I pray you, as wel becauſe iudgement in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not to you, but vnto god,<note n="t" place="margin">t. Cor. 4 4</note> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only it appertaineth to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3223:38"/> a right ſentence: as alſo becauſe the way is ſlipperie here, and men (yea otherwiſe good men) may eaſilie be deceiued.</p>
            <p>For as in perſons that are ſicke in the bodie, it ſundry times falleth out,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude.</note> that of ſom melancholike conceit in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or feare that they haue to die, they receiue the ſentence of death in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yea and ſometimes the Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons giue him ouer, and they are readye to take their leane of them, and yet God the Lord of life, ſaith they ſhal liue, and as a proofe of his power, reſtoreth them from deathes doore: ſo is it many times, with Gods children, in this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſeaſe and ſickneſſe of their ſoule, wherein as it is much more eaſie to bee miſ-led, than in bodily ſickneſſe, ſo many times when al haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſaken vs, and we haue deſtituted our ſelues, and failed in our own ſpirites, yet God the<note n="v" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3</note> God of all mercie, and father of all comfort, renueth his vnſpekeable fauour vpon vs &amp; calleth vs backe againe (as if it were) from death to life. Againe,<note place="margin">Another.</note> as men that in their owne iudgments ſeeme ſick vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3223:39"/> death, and are ſo farre from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping after health, that they can not ſo much as thinke of it, euen with ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, as many times waſt and weare awaie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d bee brought to deathes dore and yet for all that, the ſtanders by, as learned phiſitions, and faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull friendes for certaine and vndoubted tokens of happie health, and good recouerie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch doubtles is the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many diſtreſſed in conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: and amongſt the reſt, your caſe particularlie, wherein whatſoeuer you ſay of your ſelfe, or vtter againſt your ſelfe, yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t many other, (though not the beſt phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet your vnfeigned familiars) that haue nowe a long time knowne you in God, and his trueth, haue ſeene in you, ſince the daie and hower of our firſte acquaintaunce vntill this preſent time, and yet ſtill doe beho de ſuch eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie &amp; clearnes of the graces of Gods ſpirite (notwithſtanding your long and continuall complaintes) as all the ſmoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>muther, myſtes and fogges, and whatſoeuer els els that Sathan by him
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3223:39"/> ſelfe and his ſuppoſtes, hath or can caſt out againſt you, ſhall neuer bee able to take away the cleare ſight of them from vs, or mooue vs ſo much as once to doubt, of the comfortable reuiuing of them in you, euen vnto eternall lyfe. And I hope wee haue the ſpirit of God, and by the grace thereof, as alſo by the light of his Woorde, and experience that hee hath giuen vs, are able to deſerue ſome thinge in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, though not ſo well in others, as in our ſelues (for that ſhall wee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee able to doo) yet in others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to make an end where I began, Be of good comfort (good ſir) I beſeech you, and waite with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Lords ioyfull appearing, whoſe you are doubtles, and whereof you may be aſſured, becauſe you haue him<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> on your ſide, &amp; therefore not feare, who ſhal or can be againſt you: &amp; becauſe alſo you haue his children ſtanding with you and for you, not onely ſuffering the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in bodie and ſoule, that you do
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3223:40"/> and ſo learning by themſelues to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you in bonds, as thoſe that are bound with you, but with all holie comfort, as in reſpect of your ſelfe, and with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt praier, as in regard of the Lord, ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to their vttermoſt: yea becauſe he, that<note n="z" place="margin">Iames. 1.17 Gracs from God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</note> is free from ſhaddowe of tyranny, hath beſtowed ſo many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent graces of his his vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, as ſound knowledge, ſtedfaſt faith, vnfained loue, chriſtian patience, and a notable meaſure of holie obedience to his bleſſed trueth, although that in ſome of theſe, many go before you yet, in al of them I hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know any of my godly acquaintance in Chriſt, that goeth beyond you. And yet farther you may the more certainely perſwade your ſelfe of the trueth of this point, becauſe you haue caſt him ſo dear a peece, euen the hart blood of his beſt beloued ſonne, whom he hath giuen, as for the teſtification of his ſingular loue towardes man, ſo to this end alſo,<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn. 3.16</note> 
               <hi>that euerie one that beleeth in him ſhall not periſh but haue eternal life.</hi> And if that which men buy dear, they eſteem,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3223:40"/> precious, and cannot abide at any hand to haue it periſh, ſurely God will not ſee that loſt, that hee loueth ſo tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and which he hath redeemed to him ſelfe with ſo great and high a ranſome,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18</note> yea with ſuch and excellent an moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious iewell. To all which if you wil ad the manifold victories that here to fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he hath giuen you, againſt ſinne and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and all their cruell and craft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes, he euen then (as it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) moſt miraculouſly deliuering you, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor any for you, could ſo much as once dreame of a way (much leſſe beholde it) how you mighte ſcape, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie you may take it, as the voice of God from heauen, that hee will not now (ſpecially ſith hee hath vouchſafed you ſo many mercifull meanes of a ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliueraunce,) throwe you off or taſte you awaye: but deale rather with you as hee dooth with other his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes,<note n="c" place="margin">Phillip. 1.6</note> 
               <hi>make perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct in you, the good thing that he hath begunne in you, euen vntill the day of Ieſus Chriſt, and cauſe you</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 24.22</note> 
               <hi>thorow ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3223:41"/> tribulations to enter into his owne kingdome,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.25. 2. Tim 4.8 I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes. 1.12. 1. pet. 5.4</note> and crowne you there with eternall glorie.</p>
            <p>And what though you thinke it long, before the Lord come in comfort to you, yet knowe,<note n="f" place="margin">2. pet 3.</note> 
               <hi>that the Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, as ſome men count ſlacknes, but that hee that will come, wil come quicklie, and wil not tarie.</hi> His nature is not<note n="g" place="margin">pſal 103.9</note> 
               <hi>alwaies to bee chiding, neither vvill he keepe his anger for euer,</hi> (as the Prophete ſaith) Ioſeph woulde not continuallie diſſemble, his tender affection, towards his vnkinde brethren, but muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 43 30.</note> 
               <hi>breake forth into tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> and weepe vpon Beniamins necke. And ſhall wee thinke that the Lord is leſſe compaſſionate? If wee doo ſo, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie God and dallie with, yea, deceiue our owne ſoules,</p>
            <p>I denie not, but he maie for a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de his louing countenance from vs,<note place="margin">Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. 33 23.</note> and ſhewe vs after a ſorte (as it were) his darke partes, and that the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eyther to prooue our patience, in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3223:41"/> trying howe wee canne for a while forbeare that, which wee exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſire, and (as it were) hunger and thirſt after, or elſe to cauſe vs the more highlie to eſteeme of the ſame: For this is naturallie in vs, in the continuance of Gods fauours, to make little account thereof.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, this wee may aſſure our ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ues of that though<note n="k" place="margin">pſal, 30, 5</note> 
               <hi>vveeping may abide at euening, yet ioy ſhall come in the morning,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">pſal, 89, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and that his louing kindneſſe hee vvill not take from vs for euer, nor falſifie the vvoord, yea the oath that is gone out off hys mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And mee thinketh that heereof you, not onelye amongeſt, but aboue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other, ſhoulde bee throughlie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, as well by the viewe of your owne eſtate, as by the conſideration of his moſt gracious nature: wee beleeue his mercies, yea, you beleeue them, to bee ſo greate, yea ſo infinite that they cannot bee (as a man would ſay) conteyned within himſelfe, but muſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3223:42"/> of neceſſitie ere long, (euen as continuall ſpringing fountaines, that will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowe all, and make euerie thinge fruitful and pleaſaunt where they come) breake foorth and ſhewe themſelues not onely generallie to all, but in a ſpeciall maner to ſome, <hi>chieflie</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay. 66.2</note> 
               <hi>to thoſe that are poor, &amp; of contrite ſpirits</hi> tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble at his word,<note n="n" place="margin">&amp; 62.3</note> and mourn in Sion, for to ſuch is it in verie deede that the Lorde <hi>vvill looke and haue a ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongeſt the which, ſith (if I knowe any) you your ſelfe may iuſtlie bee num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred: you can not but beleeue, that you ſhall haue a plentifull portion, of thys ouerflowing fauour, becauſe you bee as certaynelye inrolled in that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as if your name were particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerlye put down.</p>
            <p>And as for your ſtate, you and wee together knowe it to bee long, tedious, and hard, where in notwithſtanding you ought to comfort your ſelfe, becauſe you are aſſured of this, and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by diligent obſeruation of naturall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3223:42"/> courſes, that there is no tempeſt or ſtorme ſo greate, but there inſueth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the necke of it, (as a man would ſay) a verye quiet calme, nor any win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo colde and deadlye, but there commeth both a ſpringing time, and ſummer alſo after: neither yet by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſome worthie partitular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alone, as Abraham, Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, and ſuch like, whoſe endes and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues you haue heard off, to bee comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and (as it were) heauenlie, but by manifolde experiences in your ſelfe, the Lord making you in your owne hearte to finde that to bee true, which as hee had promiſed in hys woord, ſo hee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye perfourmed to his ſeruauntes in all ages, and hath accompliſhed to and in you, that<note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>he wil not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you be able,</hi> (to wit, to beare thorow him) <hi>but will euen giue the iſſue with the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ye may be able to beare it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Waite therefore with all chriſtian patience, for the Lordes Spring-time and harueſt, wherein hee will come
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3223:43"/> himſelfe being reconciled vnto in Ieſus Chriſt, and comfortablie call you foorth, yea take you (as it were) by the hand, &amp; walke with you into the fieldes and ſay,<note n="p" place="margin">Cant. 2.11</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe my loue, my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire one, &amp; come thy waie, for behold vvinter is paſt, the rain is chaunged and gone away: the flovvers appeare in the earth, the time of the ſinging of birdes is come, &amp; the voice of the turtle is heard in our land:</hi> meaning vnder theſe earthlie ſimilitudes and compariſons, all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and heauenlie graces, together with the excellent fruites and effectes that by the ſame he will worke in you.</p>
            <p>Concerning which, as you muſte not bee diſcouraged, eyther with the length of time, in which they are withhelde from you, or the hardneſſe and ſharpneſſe, of the inſtrumentes and meanes, whereby they are brought to paſſe in you: ſo muſt you aſſure your ſelfe, that at the length they will come, becauſe hee is faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull, and willing and able to perfourme that hath promiſed, and their delaie doubtleſſe wil be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3223:43"/> with all manner of ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance.</p>
            <p>For euen as in huſbandrie, the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie moiſture, harde froſtes and thicke ſnowes that fall in the winter ſeaſon, doo indeede nothing els, but ſeaſon the ground, mellowing it and making it fitte for the better receiuing and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foorth alſo of that, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to it, and ſhall bee ſowen in it, howeſoeuer it ſeeme contrarie ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnto mans iudgement: So no doubt, the raine, the froſtes, the ſnow, and the iſe of your afflictions, are (as it were) not onelie prepaparatiues, for the grounde of your heart and ſoule, fitting you for, yea filling you with the pleaſaunt fruites of righteouſneſſe and religion, which are (as it were) Gods ſummer and harueſt<note n="q" place="margin">phil. 1.11</note> fruites and ſo in Chriſt, ſhallbe accounted and accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in you.</p>
            <p>Till which time come, aſſure your ſelf of this, that as he<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 14, 18.</note> wil not leaue you (alwaies or vtterly, no not very long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles, for ſo he hath faithfully promiſed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3223:44"/> in his bleſſed woorde, but when you ſeeme moſt in danger and dyſtreſſe, will viſite you, and repleniſh you with all heauenlye and holie comfort, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a moſte proper and fitte tyme for hym to woorke in, for the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his power in the eyes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the declaration of his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his owne people: ſo hee will not deſtitute you of all neceſſarye ſtrength, both to vndergoe and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome too, whatſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe him as your moſte mercifull father, nowe or elſe at anye time hereafter, to laye vppon you, or to exerciſe you withall.</p>
            <p>As for mee, loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e what due<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye it ſhall pleaſe you to preſcribe, and God ſhall vouchſafe in mercie to enable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to performe, I will not (God aiding me) fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e therein: yea, I ſay vnto you, not onely vſe me, but commaund me in the ſame, and if you finde mee not therein readie to my vttermoſt, I am content you ſhall write me vp with ſuch diſſembling and faithleſſe friends,
<pb facs="tcp:3223:44"/> as abound almoſt euerie where.</p>
            <p>This I promiſe, and by his ſtrength, that muſt performe all in all, I hope I ſhall accompliſh that I will not ceaſe in my poore meaſure to pray for you, till ſuch time, as I ſhall vnderſtand, that as by manie other meanes, ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by that, God himſelfe ſhalbe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to beſtowe vpon you your full deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: and I haue occaſion to yeeld him humble thankes, for graunting the graces that I &amp; others, as on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, haue ſoundly (though in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and wantes) prayed vnto him for.</p>
            <p>And thus with hartie thanks for your manifold and continuall kindneſſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me and mine, and humble ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in Chriſt, vnto you, and your good bedfellowe miſtreſſe H. I doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly commend you to the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whoſe ſith you whollie are, and to whome ſith your heauenly father, hath giuen you to be kept, I doubt not but you ſhal continue faſt and remaine ſure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en vnto the end, not onely becauſe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o whom you are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted for cuſtodie,<note n="s" place="margin">Math. 28.18,</note>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:3223:45"/> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Math, 28, 18</note> 
               <hi>hath al povver giuen vnto him,</hi> both in heauen and earth, but alſo becauſe we knowe, in the trueth of his worde that is the trueth it ſelf,<note n="t" place="margin">Iohn 10.12</note> that he looſeth none of thoſe, that are committed vnto him,<note n="u" place="margin">&amp; 6.37.</note> nor caſteth anie ſuch away as come vnto him. At London the laſt of this May. 1589.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips, as bounden, ſo readie alwayes in all that he may. T.W. the Lords moſt vnworthy ſeruant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:3223:45"/>
            <head>GRACE AND PEACE from God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) if my poore iudgement deceiue me not,<note place="margin">The afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſpirite moſt grieuous.</note> manifolde proofs of this point that the afflictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the ſpirite, are muche more great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd grieuous than the diſeaſes or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les of the outward man. For firſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olie Ghoſt himſelfe in plaine tearmes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffirmeth it, ſaying:<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 18.14.</note> The ſpirite of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man will ſuſtayne his infirmitie, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing thereby, his outward paines and griefes of what nature or kinde ſoeuer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut a wounded ſpirite who can beare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: vnderſtanding thereby the troubles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the hart or ſoule, ſpeaking as though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee ſhoulde ſaie it is not onely a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard thing to performe, but that verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>we alſo are found, that can indeede
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3223:46"/> indure it, yea none but ſuche, as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſome ſpecial grace from God himſelfe. Secondly, the verie lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table complaintes and earneſt prayers, that Gods Children (who indeede are moſte, I had almoſt ſaid onely exerciſed that way, this I am ſure of, with fruite and profite) haue eſpeciallie in that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed caſe, made and powred forth, doe plainlie proue it. Take Dauid &amp; Paul, in ſtead of manie, or all if you will: the one auouching that there<note n="b" place="margin">Pſalm. 38.3.</note> was nothing ſound in his fleſhe becauſe of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neither reſt in his bones by reaſon of his ſinne: and the other crying out,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?<note place="margin">By fearefull effectes.</note> Thirdly the fearefull effectes, that the one bringeth foorth more than the other, it taking for the time, appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite from the ſtomake, ſleepe from the eye, hearing from the eare, and all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of delight, lawfull and vnlawfull, outward and inward from the whole man, as particular examples of Gods ſaintes doe manifeſtly ſhewe (for which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3223:46"/> ſee the places quoted in the margine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.2.3.4. &amp;c. Pſal. 102.3.4 5.6.7. &amp;c.</note> and ſome ſuch like) and experience in our ſelues (if euer we haue bene in that eſtate) or the condition of other men (if wee haue heedily obſerued it) will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently warrant the ſame vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Neither yet are theſe thinges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, to diſmaie and diſcourage thoſe that are after that ſorte exerciſed, for ſurely their afflictions and troubles, be hard and heauie inough, and indeede doe rather craue all maner of comfort, than anie depreſſing at all their ſinne, and the ſight of the ſame, with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Gods iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them for it, beeing as the Prophet ſaith in another Pſalme (vz. 38.4. gone ouer their head, and become as a weightie burthen, to heauie for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beare: or to throwe downe aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure when they come to it, ſuch as haue not entred into that courſe or combate. For howſoeuer as yet, they haue not felt weakeneſſe or wantes in themſelues, or Gods ſtrength aſſiſting them agaynſt ſinne, yet then ſhall they finde that true
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3223:47"/> that the Apoſtle ſayth,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13</note> that God is faithull and will not ſuffer them to bee tempted aboue that they are able, but will euen giue the iſſue with the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that they may be able to beare it: or to ſtop anie from ſtriuing, to yeeld to particular perſons in that diſtreſſe, anie reliefe or comfort that God hath giuen them themſelues, for that were to cauſe them to neglect, the beſt duties of holie loue towardes men in their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, we being enioyned by the Lord, to<note n="e" place="margin">Galat. 6.2</note> beare one an others burthen,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 12, 15</note> and to weepe with them that weepe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue themſelues of comfort, in the daies of the like daunger, for howe can they looke to be pitied, that haue had no care to expreſſe the ſame to others.</p>
            <p>But rather to comfort them that are afflicted, and that euen in the greatneſſe of their griefe whileſt they ſee no<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor, 10, 13</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temptation to haue taken holde of them, but ſuch as appertaineth to man, yea to the beſt men that haue bene in this life, which alſo the greater they are, the more are they therein conformed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3223:47"/> vnto the<note n="h" place="margin">Rom, 8.17</note> image of the ſonne of God Ieſus Chriſt in his ſufferinges: who patiently vnderwent, and mightily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame (not onely for himſelfe, but for vs) all that that we beare but in part, &amp; yet ſhal at the laſt thorow him, be in and of the ſame<note n="i" place="margin">29</note> more than conquerours: and to prepare others before they come into thoſe conflicts, that ſo, neither an imagination of their own ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth neuer as yet aſſaied, nor a conceit of the weake force of the foe, neuer well felt, nor the vnwontedneſſe of the troubles that they muſt indure, nor the greatneſſe or length of the trials that they are to ſuſtain,<note n="k" place="margin">Epheſ, 6.10 11. &amp;c.</note> nor any other thing whatſoeuer may caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, much leſſe ouercome them, but prouoke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather to be prepared in the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of God, the power of his word, and the might of his ſpirite, valiantly to encounter with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame<note n="l" place="margin">Luke, 21, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> lifting vp their heads &amp; harts knowing that the time of their redemption draweth nigh: &amp; to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and ſtir vp the laſt ſort, in al chriſtian pitie &amp; bowels of compaſſion, to inlarge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to their vttermoſt, yea beyond,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3223:48"/> it, if they coulde tell howe, towards ſuch afflicted ſoules, that ſo according to the<note n="m" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.4.</note> conſolations, which they themſelues haue receiued from God, they may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter comfort vnto others diſtreſſed, perſwading themſelues further of this that the more hard the cure and worke is, (ſpeciallie if they feele the ſame left them, as a ſpurre to pricke them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) the more glorie ſhall thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound vnto God (the<note n="n" place="margin">Phillip. 2.13. Iames. 1.17.</note> onely worker and giuer of all good thinges) and the more comfort to themſelues, whome God hath bin pleaſed to vſe, as worthie inſtrumentes, &amp; that not in ſome meane affaire or buſineſſe, but in this great du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of comforting the diſtreſſed,<note n="o" place="margin">Iud. 23.</note> and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them with feare, pulling them out of the fire.</p>
            <p>Nowe as by that which hath bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie deliuered, wee may ſenſibly ſee a difference betweene bodily afflictions, and the inward ſorrowes of a troubled ſpirite: ſo it is not to be doubted, but that euen amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thoſe inward griefs, temptations and aſſaultes, that ſuch
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3223:48"/> indure, ſome are more ſharpe, and ſore than other ſome, though indeede the leaſt and ſhorteſt of them, be verie grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous to fleſh and bloud (or to ſpeake as the Apoſtle doth<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 12, 11</note> no chaſtiſement for the preſent ſeemeth to bee ioyous, but grieuous rather) I will not ſay to bear, for I ſuppoſe verily euerie man will confeſſe it, but euen to thinke of: which were the point doubtfull wee might la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to proue but being a manifeſt and confeſſed trueth, it ſhall not be amiſſe to ſpare that pains, and to trauaile in that, which is ſomewhat more hard, and may be of much better vſe.</p>
            <p>Amongeſt thoſe troubles of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man that are greateſt indeede, none in my ſimple iudgement, fitteth more nigh to, or pincheth or preſſeth more hard the hearts of the deare ſaints and ſeruauntes of God, in the dayes of their fleſhe and combating, than the ſight or memorie of the fearefull ſinnes that they haue committed againſt hys bleſſed maieſtie: which alſo as they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate vnto themſelues, not onely in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3223:49"/> their owne nature, that is to ſay, as they are ſinnes, and violations or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the law of God, but in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, place, perſons, and maner of doing, as that they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the daies of knowledge, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, and by men of great note &amp; name &amp;c. all which doth adde vnto iniquitie, &amp; cauſeth the ſame to be more grieuous, ſo they increaſe it vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter effects they bring forth, as ſeparation between God and man, a taint and curſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the creatures, horror of heart in our ſelues, infirmities vpon the fleſh, temporall &amp; eternall death both of bodie and ſoule, without great grace &amp; ſingular fauor from almighty god, &amp;c. in all which reſpects, the weake heart had neede to be<note n="g" place="margin">Can. 2.5 1. Theſſ. 5.14</note> ſtayed, leaſt it faint and fall downe without hope of ryſing vp, and the wounded ſpirite calleth indeede, for ſome of the wine and oyle of God to be powred thereinto, leaſt otherwiſe it feſter and become irrecouerable.</p>
            <p>But againſt al and euery one of theſe (though ſore, aſſaultes I confeſſe) we
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3223:49"/> ſhall ſee that we haue ſingular and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conſolations, and that not fewe in number alone, and theſe weake and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo, but manie and the ſame verie mightie, yea euerie one of them ſtrong and ſufficient it ſelfe, to beate backe this aſſault, though it were muche more powerfull and forcible, then it is, that ſo being compaſſed about, and as it were backed with ſuch a<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 12.1</note> cloud of witneſſes, our hartes might be the more ſtedfaſtly vp held not onely in preſent comfort, but in hope of all good thinges to come.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, that whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the father himſelfe, who otherwiſe<note n="s" place="margin">1, Tim. 6, 16</note> dwelling in light, that no man can come vnto, hath yet notwithſtanding plentifullie and plainely reuealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto vs in his word: or by the eye of a ſtedfaſt faith looke vppon Ieſus Chriſt his ſon and our ſauior, who is alſo the brightneſſe of the glory and the<note n="t" place="margin">Hebrew. i. 3.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen forme of his perſon: or regard the bleſſed word of almightie God, in all the parts and peeces of it, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the promiſes thereof propounded
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3223:50"/> for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort: or conſider as we ſhould and are bound,<note place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. 1 Cor. 10.1.2.3. &amp;c. Rom, 4.11.</note> the holy ſacraments that he hath giuen vs in this world, as pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his goodnes toward vs, &amp; ſeales of the faithe, that hee hath wrought in vs, or might well as wee ought, that right order of diſcipline &amp; gouernment,<note place="margin">Diſcipline of the Church.</note> that he hath eſtabliſhed in his Churche, for the repreſſing of euill, or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of all well dooing: or diligently marke the ſingular fauors that hee hath plentifullie ſhedde out vpon thoſe, that haue gone before vs in the fleſhe, and in the faith: or ſee and feele the great gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that hee of his owne good will hath beſtowed vppon vs our ſelues poore and miſerable wretches that wee are: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with a ſound iudgement ſin it ſelfe, ſpecially, as in regard of the good, that God maketh to flowe from it (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be odious and vglie in it ſelfe) we ſhall certainely finde, that from all and euerie one of theſe, wee may without doubt gather ſtrong argumentes and forcible reaſons, aſſured and continuall comfort, for the forgiueneſſe of all our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3223:50"/> ſins, &amp; by conſequent alſo for the ſound and Chriſtian peace of our own hearts.</p>
            <p>Nowe to the ende, that that which hath bene generallie ſpoken, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliuered may yet appeare to bee as true and certaine, ſo plentiful and large, let vs come more particularly, and at length (as it were) yet without tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, to deduct and laie out theſe poyntes.</p>
            <p>For the firſt we haue the verie mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull nature,<note place="margin">Of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God himſelfe.</note> and readie inclination of almighty God in himſelfe to ſhew pitie and compaſſion, to thoſe that are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, who howſoeuer he declare himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf in word and deede armed, and that with iuſtice againſt the proud Phariſee, or benummed and ſenſeleſſe profeſſor, as he hath good cauſe indeede, for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſinne, and want of a tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpirite, ſtandeth yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in his fatherly compaſſion and loue, moſte graciouſly affected, to ſuch as quake and ſloupe before him. Which that we might be the better perſwaded of, he hath bene pleaſed plainly to tel vs,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3223:51"/> and that in his holie worde alſo that hee hath no deſire that<note n="u" place="margin">Ezech. 18, 23</note> the wicked ſhoulde die, but rather that hee ſhould liue: and againe, that hee is the<note n="x" place="margin">Exod. 34, 6, 7</note> Lord, ſtrong, mercifull and gracious, ſlowe to anger, and aboundant to goodneſſe and trueth, reſeruing mercie for thouſandes, forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing iniquittes and tranſgreſſions, &amp;c. and that he wil giue to ſuch as<note n="y" place="margin">Iſaiah, 61.3</note> mourne in Sion, bewtie for aſhes, and the oyle of ioy for mourning, and the garment of gladneſſe, for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, or as it is in the prophet Ezechiell<note n="z" place="margin">Ezek. 9, 4, &amp;c.</note> a marke, by which they ſhalbe known and freed from the common calamitie and deſtruction of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Of the trueth of all which wee may bee the better aſſured, becauſe it is the worde, not of a mortall man, who will in the hypocriſie and corruption of hys heart doubt and diſſemble, but of the eternall God, (who as he is not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo doth hee not deceiue, and who beeing of an vnchaungeable nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth faſt and ſure) and the ſame with a cleare voyce, and in wordes of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3223:51"/> muche euidencie publiſhed and proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not once and awaie (for then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in the diſtruſtfulneſſe of our owne heartes wee might quickly call it into queſtion)<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 86, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. 103.8.9 The ſonne of God and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</note> but ſundrie times, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie places of his holy word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, who ſeeth not, that euen in Ieſus Chriſt, wee haue a mercifull meaſure of ſpirituall comfort, preſſed downe and running euer againſt this ſharpe temptation and ſore aſſault? and that not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, becauſe as he is God, he is<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 9.5</note> able to forgiue ſinnes, and as man being<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 2, 17</note> made like vnto his brethren, hee is pitifull and readie for that and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good workes, but alſo becauſe in him dwelleth,<note n="d" place="margin">Colloſſ. 2, 9</note> al the fulneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily, we hauing in him<note n="e" place="margin">Colloſſ. 1, 14</note> redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thorowe his bloud, that as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, in whome likewiſe<note n="f" place="margin">2, Cor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 20</note> all the promiſes of God, are yea and amen, hee himſelfe being made of God vnto vs<note n="g" place="margin">1, Cor, 1, 30</note> wiſdom, &amp; righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification &amp; redemption: who alone was<note n="h" place="margin">Iſaiah, 53, 5</note> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for our tranſgreſſions, &amp; broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our iniquitie, bearing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3223:52"/> of our peace, &amp; healing vs thorowe his ſtripes he himſelfe and nowe other<note place="margin">&amp; 63.3</note> treading the wine preſſe of gods wrath agaynſt vs for our ſinnes: whome ſith God hath bene pleaſed to<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> giue vnto death for vs all: howe ſhall he not toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him giue vs all thinges alſo? If all things, why not then the free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and ful forgiueneſſe of all our ſins? Shal you imagine that God wil ſay al, &amp; giue vs but ſome? that were to make him a lier, who is not<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4</note> onely true, but truth it ſelfe. Or ſhall we deeme that for the teſtification of the largeneſſe of hys liberality, he wil vouchſafe vs ſome pety fauours, and withhold graces of muche greater excellencie? that were to make god deale worſe with his dear children, then earthlie princes do, with their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſeruants. I ſay therfore againe if all things, why not remiſſion of ſinnes, ſpeciallie ſith in him are hidde (yet ſo as they daylie are plainelie, and in good time ſhall bee plentifullie diſplaied, and aboundantlie, yea perfectlie communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vnto his people)<note n="m" place="margin">Colloſſ. 2, 3</note> all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3223:52"/> of wiſedome, knowledge, mercy, and whatſoeuer els is excellent in God, as in reſpect of himſelfe, or comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and profitable, as in regard of vs.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, the bleſſed booke of God it ſelfe, doeth in the holie commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of it call vs, and in the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table promiſes thereunto adioyned, and conteyned therein allowe vs, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the haynouſneſſe and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe of our ſinnes, yea the rather for that (becauſe without the ſenſe of it, neither can we well perceiue our owne eſtate and miſerie, nor effectually feele the excellencie and riches of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and fauour) to<note n="n" place="margin">Iames. 4.</note> draw nigh vnto God that ſo he may draw nigh vnto vs, who neuer thruſteth them backe, much leſſe driueth them awaie that come vnto him.</p>
            <p>In the olde teſtament none ſeemeth vnto me more plaine and pregnant, then theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in the book of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet I ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holie ghoſt ther ſaying:<note n="o" place="margin">Iſay. i 18</note> Come now and let vs reaſon together ſaith the lord: though your ſinnes were as crymoſin,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3223:53"/> they ſhal be made white as ſnow: though they were redde as Scarlet, they ſhall be as wooll. And in an other place<note n="p" place="margin">Iſay. 55.1.</note> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euery one that is thirſtie, come ye to the waters: and ye that haue no ſiluer, come buy &amp; eat: Come I ſay, buy wine and milke without ſiluer, and without money.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In the new Teſt.</note>And in the new Teſtament, theſe of our ſauiour Chriſt which is the eternall wiſedome of the eternall father are moſt comfortable and ſweet ſayings,<note n="q" place="margin">Math. 7.7</note> Aſke, and it ſhall be geuen you, ſeeke, and ye ſhall find, knocke and it ſhall bee opened vnto you: and againe<note n="r" place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note>: Come vnto me all ye that are wearie and heauie laden, and I will eaſe you: Take my yoake on you, &amp;c. and you ſhal find reſt vnto your ſoules, for my yoke is eaſie, &amp; my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then light. What can be more lightfull or delightfull? By this commandement we knowe, that our comming to him, ſhall bee accepted of him, for hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth not the dooing of that which he abhorreth: And by the promiſes wee are incouraged, yea aſſured to receiue, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3223:53"/> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> no one iot or tytle of his woord, much leſſe his faithful promiſes ſhal fall to the ground, &amp; it is yet more and more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed vnto vs, in the perſon of of him that ſpeaketh it, I meane Ieſus Chriſt, who being<note n="t" place="margin">Iohn. 1.18</note> in the boſome of the father, hath fully reuealed him &amp; al his wil vnto vs.</p>
            <p>As for the ſacraments,<note place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; the end why the they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned.</note> the very cauſe &amp; end of their inſtitution, doth propound comfort vnto vs in this point, they being ordained by God, &amp; appointed to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in his Church, not only to put vs in mind of him and his graces, but to be as helpes &amp; aides to guide our weak faith to Chriſt himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, yea to make vs partakers of him, &amp; all his merites, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the forgiuenes of our ſins. In who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſith there is not onely of himſelfe all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but that that alſo is true,<note n="v" place="margin">Iohn 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6</note> which is els where ſpoken in the Scripture of him, that of his fulneſſe wee haue all receiued, and grace for grace, that is, grace vpon grace, or graces heaped one vppon another, or (as a man woulde ſaie) all aboundaunce of all manner
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3223:54"/> of grace, we may aſſure our ſelues, that with him and in him, we ſhall finde thys grace of the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and eternall life alſo, becauſe as there is no other ſacrifice, for remiſſion of ſinnes, but he alone as the Apoſtle plainelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in the epiſtle to the Hebrues, ſo ther is no other<note n="x" place="margin">Act 4. i2.</note> name geuen vnder heauen wherein men muſt bee ſaued, but the name of Ieſus.</p>
            <p>That which is ſpoken indefinitlie of both the ſacraments together, ſhal better appeare in the particular conſiderat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of them by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and a part.</p>
            <p>Concerning baptiſme, Gods ſpirit in many places affirmeth, that it<note place="margin">Baptiſme.</note> ſaueth vs (which yet leaſt any ſhold ty to the deed done,<note n="c" place="margin">Mark. 16.16.</note> it adioineth with it faith, the<note n="z" place="margin">Titus 3.5</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing that is wrought in vs by the holy ghoſt, &amp; termeth it,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Peter 3.21</note> not a putting away of the filth of the fleſh, but a confident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience maketh to god) which yet it could not do without for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giuenes of ſins before going,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 15.50</note> for fleſh &amp; blood cannot inherit eternal life: but to what end we vrge this ſith Peter Acts 2
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3223:54"/> ſaith, be baptiſed euerie one of you in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And that which the ſeruant ſayth (yet by the ſpirite of God) touching Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that the maiſter himſelfe (<note n="d" place="margin">Iohn. 4.34 The Supper.</note> who hath not the ſpirite by meaſure) auoucheth in plaine tearmes touching the ſupper, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note n="e" place="margin">Math. 26.28</note> this is my bloud of the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that is ſhed for many, for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And that the holie Diſcipline of the Church it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Diſcipline of the Church.</note> ſhould affoord vs much comfort againſt this temptation, who is it that either can, will, or dare denie, that will either conſider the author of it, euen God himſelfe in Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 56.5.15</note> moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to mercy and of great goodnes? or the endes whereunto it was orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it being appointed not onely for the preuention of euill,<note n="g" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.14</note> in the ſeuerall members and whole bodie, but for the<note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.20</note> gaining of men vnto God, euen after ſinne and tranſgreſſion, hath en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red or preuailed, they being<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor, 5.5</note> chaſtiſed a little in this life, that their ſoules might bee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3223:55"/> ſaued in the daie of Chriſt: or the perſons exerciſing or executing the ſame, that is the Church, and ſuch woorthie men therein as the Church from among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for their rare excellent graces be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon them from God, haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vnto themſelues, who hauing not onelie the promiſe of the preſence of god, that is, that<note n="k" place="margin">Mark. 18.20</note> wherſoeuer two or three are gathered together in his name, hee is in the middeſt of them, but alſo the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and direction thereof, for where the ſpirite is, there is power alſo, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receiue &amp; admit vpon repentance, euen as the Lord himſelfe: whereof that we our ſelues might be the better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the holy ghoſt hath bin pleaſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into their handes, and to giue vnto them power alſo<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn. 20.23.</note> to abſolue, &amp; to looſe ſuch as are bruiſed in ſpirite, and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a godlie ſorrow for their ſin: yea for the further ſtrengthening of our weake faith therein, hee hath not onelie graunted them and vs together with them, his moſt certaine promiſe,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 18.18</note> that whatſoeuer they looſe on earth ſhall be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3223:55"/> looſed in heauen, hee meaning thereby a moſt ſufficient and full confirmation thereof, ratifieng it as verelie to our ſpirites, euen as though we had heard hys owne voyce ſpeaking vnto vs out of the cloudes, but alſo hath left vs ſome example of it in the Woord, and that not of one man committing ſome ſmal tranſgreſſion, or petie ſinor offence (as wee ſay) but ſuch<note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.1</note> iniquitie as is not heard of, no not among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that one ſhoulde haue his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wyfe: Concerning which facte, and reconciliation vppon repentaunce for the ſame, the Apoſtle ſaieth els where,<note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 6.72</note> 
               <hi>It is ſufficient for the ſame man, that hee was rebuked of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:</hi> ſo that nowe contrariwiſe you ought rather to forgiue him, and to comfort him, leaſte the ſame ſhoulde be ſwallowed vppe with ouer much heauineſſe, wherefore I praye you that you would confirme your loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hym.</p>
            <p>In the holie ſcriptures or woorde of God, we haue infinit ſtore of examples,<note place="margin">Examples of Gods mercie,</note>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:3223:56"/> and bee compaſſed about on euerie ſide, (as it were)<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 12.1</note> with a thick cloude of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which both for their multitude, and for their faithfulneſſe, are greater then al expectation, and to whom for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and in whom for others, God hath bene pleaſed plentifullie to declare as the riches of his mercie generallie, ſo particularly, that he<note n="q" place="margin">Deut. 7.9 2 Chron. 6.5</note> hath kept faith and trueth with them, and will doe ſo for euer with al thoſe that ſucceed them in faith and a<note place="margin">Iame. 1.17</note> good conſcience, that ſo our hope and harte might relie vppon him alone, with whom is no variable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither ſhall neuer turne. Let two verie woorthy and plaine (one wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in the olde, and the other in the newe Teſtament) ſerue for all?<note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5 Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.3</note> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid from an vnfeigned heart acknowled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth it, and that more then once, that the Lord in the multitude of his mercies, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue both the puniſhment of his ſinne, and all his iniquitie whatſoeuer. And Paule with a franke and free mouth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlie confeſſeth, and that others might heare it and beleeue it, ſaith.<note n="t" place="margin">1. Timoh. 1.15</note> This is a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3223:56"/> faithfull ſaying, and woorthy by all meanes to be receiued, that Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt came into the world to ſaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ers, of whom I am chiefe.</p>
            <p>And if wee reſpect their perſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were men notwithſtanding their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s, dearelie beloued of God: the one taken<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 8.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> by the Lord from the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ewes with yong, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed his people in Iacob, &amp; the other pulled from perſecuting the church, to preach &amp; to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Lords name among the gentil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.<note n="u" place="margin">Act. 9.15</note>
            </p>
            <p>If we conſider the ſins that they ſpeak of, we ſhall find them no leſſe<note n="x" place="margin">2. Sam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, murther,<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam 24.</note> pride,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, oppreſſion, &amp; ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dry ſuch like. If we regard the ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dnes &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of their hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, they ſpeaking &amp; deliuering that, as withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a mind doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe to deceiue ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſo without parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie and reſpect as in regard of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and euen as they fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour for themſelues, &amp; for others, we can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not chooſe but beleeue it, &amp; that we haue our part &amp; portion in it, &amp; the rath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath geuen vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3223:57"/> like holy examples to be (as it wer) ſeals ſet vnto the promiſes, for the more ſtrong eſtabliſhing of the ſame in our hearts, we perſwading our ſelues, that as we may and ought to profit by the preſidents of gods<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11</note> iudgement, to work in vs vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned feare &amp; reuerence of his maieſty, and care of a better courſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer we haue practiſed:<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 15.4</note> ſo we ſhal make vſe of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of his mercy, to ſtyr vs vp, &amp; to make in vs a holy feeling of all ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; heauenly ioy. And that the graces of Gods holy ſpirite,<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit.</note> which hee himſelfe in Chriſt hath bin pleaſed plentifully to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon vs, &amp; mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e particularly, that our<note n="c" place="margin">Iude. 20.</note> precious &amp; holy fa th, together with the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rall fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts &amp; ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cts that flow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſhold pledge vnto vs this great fauour of God in the forgiuenes of our ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, thorow the death &amp; obedience of his ſonne, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as cleare as the ſunne in his glorie and brightneſſe: and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, if that which is from ſinne, and from our ſelues, may iuſtlie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs and beat vs downe, then that which proceedeth from God who is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3223:57"/> 
               <hi>d</hi> greater than all, and <hi>e</hi> onely good, can not chooſe, but being liuely felt and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie perceiued, but raiſe vs vp againe, alſo becauſe the ſcripture it ſelf, in terms that will admit no darke or doubtfull interpretation aduoucheth that God<note n="f" place="margin">2, Cor, 8.12</note> accepteth vs according to that wee haue, and not according to that wee haue not.</p>
            <p>For fayth, wee haue amongſt others that comfortabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> promiſe of holie writte.<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fayth.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Haba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.4 Rom 1.17</note> The iuſt ſhall liue by fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, which can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be vnderſtood of life here, as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tune to come as al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo becauſe as in reſpect of brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in this world, the wicked haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as well as the godly, and we knowe that it was the Lords purpoſe by his ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, in that ſpeach to diſcerne betweene<note n="h" place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 22.26</note> the pretious and the vile.</p>
            <p>If we well conſider,<note place="margin">Vnfained l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue</note> either the loue that God hath wrought in our heartes towards his ſaintes, or the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ygned mind, that thorow his great goodnes we find in our ſelues, to forget and forgeue other mens treſpaſſes, wee ſhall finde
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3223:58"/> that to the one &amp; the other may giue vs firme hope, &amp; aſſured comfort of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of our own ſins: the holy ghoſt affirming of the former, that by this we<note n="i" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.14</note> know wee are tranſlated from death vnto life, becauſe we loue the brethren: &amp; for the other, our ſauiour himſelfe, not only teaching vs to ſay,<note n="k" place="margin">Math. 6.12</note> forgiue vs our treſpaſſes as we forgiue them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas againſt vs but alſo declaring in plain tearmes, that except wee forgiue from our heartes each one to his brother his treſpaſſes,<note n="l" place="margin">Math. 18 3i</note> ther is no forgiuenes of ours before God, declaring withal, that wher that is, the other cannot bee wanting, becauſe God is not onelye much more readye, but infinitely much more able, to ſhewe ſinners that notable fauour then men are ſo manifeſt it one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Wherein it ſhall not bee amiſſe for vs to marke this further,<note place="margin">Of merits.</note> that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the good things we are enabled to no, cannot as they come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs nor yet of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in that reſpect mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Gods mercie becauſe<note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 64.6</note> al our righteouſneſſes
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3223:58"/> are as filthie and ſtained cloutes before him, &amp;<note n="n" place="margin">Luke. 17.10</note> when we haue done al that we can, wee are yet vnprofitable ſeruants) much leſſe any one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeperated from the reſt, the weaknes whereof ariſing, not from the good things themſelues in their owne nature, &amp; as they come from God, (for ſo they are and muſt be verie ſtrong, &amp; exceeding good) but by reaſon of our corruption, &amp; the imperfection y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thorow the ſame cleaueth therto, yet all of them together, and euery one of them ſelues may bee effectual pledges vnto vs, as of Gods great fauor ſhed abroad into our harts, ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowning of thoſe his graces in vs with wonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful honour, and glorious immortality at the laſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie it ſeemeth vnto me,<note place="margin">Of ſin it ſelf.</note> that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en from ſinne it ſelfe, though not in it owne nature, for ſo it is abhominable in the Lords ſight,<note n="o" place="margin">Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.13</note> whoſe pure eies cannot ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e euill, neither yet in the, effects that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it bringeth foorth, for ſo is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bytter, making a fearefull<note n="p" place="margin">Iſaiah. 59.2.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration betweene the Lord and vs, &amp; hauing for the<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 6.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> wages of it, eternal death
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3223:59"/> and damnation, yet euen in the heynouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and heyght thereof, being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with gods fauour in the forgiuenes of the ſame, we ſhould &amp; may reap an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible argument, of much conſolation and ſingular comfort.</p>
            <p>For wherein ſhal or can the mercy of God in this life, ſo much appear towards his people, as in pardoning the ſinnes of his ſeruants? To whom had they not offended neither could gods mercie that way foorth, haue bin declared, nor Chriſt for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue bin<note n="r" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> God manifeſted in the fleſh, who therefore came into the world, not to call<note n="s" place="margin">Math. 9.13.</note> the righteous, but ſinners to repentaunce, and did therefore appeare amongeſt men, not onely that he might<note n="t" place="margin">1, Ioh. 3.5.8.</note> looſe the works of the deuil, but alſo that he might take away our ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Outward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods fauour.</note>All the outward fauours that wee haue in this life, if we ſhould reckon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp, one by one, as for example creation, preſeruation, health, wealth, &amp;c. or binde them all in a bundle together, cannot ſo ſenſibly ſet before vs Gods loue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome of them are in ſome ſort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:3223:59"/> to other creatures with men, &amp; reach but to the bodie for the moſt part, &amp; this time preſent onely, the wicked many times beeing before Gods ſaintes in ſome of the ſame, God alſo<note n="v" place="margin">Pſ 17.14</note> filling their bellies with his hid treaſure, their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren hauing inough, and leauing inough of their ſubſtance for their children.<note place="margin">Spiritual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, I will ſay more, many of thoſe ſpirituall graces that God vouchſaſeth vnto his Church, as h s worde, ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; praier, of which the holy ghoſt ſaith, he<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 147.19</note> ſheweth his word vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes and his iudgments vnto Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, and he hath not dealt ſo with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie nation, doe not ſo plain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iy ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe the fauour and loue of the Lorde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hys people, as the free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and full forgiueneſſe of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: the reaſon is, becauſe<note n="y" place="margin">Math 22.14</note> manye are called, and fewe are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and diuers bee in the Churche, that bee not of the Church: This grace alſo extending it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to bodye and ſoule in ſays lyfe, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with it comfort and the peace of a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3223:60"/> good conſcience here, but reaching euen vnto the life that is to come, eternal ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and life euerlaſting, being an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable companion, to the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And that we might the better be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that this is a verie ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, God himſelfe taketh vpon himſelf as a principall point of his glory, this great worke of forgiuing, laying<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaiah. 42.25</note> I, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I am he that putteth away thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities for my owne ſake, and will not remember thy ſinnes. And in an other Prophet rehearſing the graces, that he will vouchſafe vnto his people in the newe Teſtament, he reckoneth vp this as the laſt and chiefeſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Iere 31 34.</note> I wil forgiue their iniquitie<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.20</note>, and remember their ſinne no more, that beeing true here, that the Apoſtle ſaieth, that where ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded there grace abounded much more.</p>
            <p>To conclude then (good Madam) out of all that is gone before.<note place="margin">The co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h in thys poynt of the forgiuenes of ſins God who is greater than al is<note n="b" place="margin">Rom, 8, 3</note> on our ſide, &amp;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3223:60"/> therefore wee neede not care who be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs: Ieſus Chriſt ſtandeth for vs, who is<note n="c" place="margin">Math, 3, 17</note> his dearely beloued ſonne, in whome onely hee is well pleaſed, and thorow whome he hath<note n="d" place="margin">2, Cor, 3, 19</note> reconciled the world vnto himſelfe. the word generally &amp; part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cularly the promiſes in the ſame, which are in Ieſus Chriſt<note n="e" place="margin">2, Cor, 1, 20</note> yea and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeake comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>table things vnto vs: the holy ſacramentes ordeined by God for the ſtrengthning of our weake faith, ſeale vp that great and gracious fauor vnto vs: the diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pline and voyce of the Church, which is the<note n="f" place="margin">1, Tim, 3, 16</note> piller &amp; ground of trueth, and (as it were) Gods owne voyce from heauen, confirmeth it: the particular examples o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſaintes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in former time found it and felt it true, doe ratifie and confirme the ſame: the peculiar fauo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that God hath giuen vs our ſelues in this life, and namely faith<note n="g" place="margin">2, Theſſ, 3, 2</note> (which all men haue not) with the ſound tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes thereof, doe pledge it vp: and that god that maketh the<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal, 76, 10</note> rage of men to turne to his praiſe, and in the beginning comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded<note n="i" place="margin">2, Cor. 4, 6,</note> the light to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3223:61"/> ſhine out of darkeneſſe, now maketh ſin to ſerue, for the magnifying and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting of his mercie, and the comfort and good of his children who is it that can diſtruſt? or rather who hath not iuſt cauſe, with the Apoſtles and ſaintes of God, to ſing and ſay,<note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.54.55.56.57</note> death is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp into victorie, O deathe where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie? The ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the lawe. But thanks be to God, which hath giuen vs victorie, thorow our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And againe:<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 8, 38, 39.</note> I am perſwaded that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death nor life, nor angels nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor powers nor thinges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor thinges to come, nor height, nor dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, nor anie other creature, ſhalbe able to ſeparate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus (good Madame) I haue (as your honour ſeeth) plainely deliuered my poore iudgement, in this worthie point, touching the comfortable feeling of the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and ſome ſuch aſſured ſeales and pledges of the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3223:61"/> ſame, as by<note n="m" place="margin">Deut. 17, 18, 19, Ioſhua. 1, 8 Pſalm. 1.2. Iohn, 5, 39,</note> dayly reading of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſcriptures, and continuall meditation in the ſame, (holie duties that I and all other chriſtians, of what qualitie or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo euer, are bound vnto by Gods word to performe: and woulde to God all did it, as may knowe and confeſſe it) the Lorde in much fauor, I freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, hath bene pleaſed in the dayes of my diſtreſſe, to manifeſt to me, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable man that I am, and that not onely for inſtruction and comfort vnto my ſelf alone (for God neuer beſtoweth anie grace vpon vs, much leſſe ſuch excellent fauors, to that ende onely) but for the good and conſolation of others, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="n" place="margin">2, Cor. 1, 3 4,</note> the father of mercies and God of all comfort, doth not onely comfort vs in all our tribulations, but alſo inableth vs to comfort them, which are in anie affliction, by the comfort wherewith we our ſelues are comforted of him, what it is I will not affirme, becauſe the holie Ghoſt hath taught mee ſaying:<note n="o" place="margin">Prouer. 27.2</note> let an other man prayſe thee, and not thyne owne mouthe, a ſtraunger
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3223:62"/> and not thine owne lips, yet ſure I am of this that Gods trueth it is, and vpon the certaine perſwaſion that I haue thereof, I ſhalbe readie (the Lord aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting me) not onely to confeſſe it wholie and in all places, and before all perſons, but Chriſt Ieſus guiding me, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting me<note n="p" place="margin">Iohn. 15.5</note> without whom I cannot do any thing to laie downe my ſelfe, and to ſeale (as if it were) with my bloud the certaintie of the ſame.</p>
            <p>What effect it may bring forth in your honor (at whoſe religious requeſt I was vnfeignedly forward and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to vndertake theſe trauailes, which alſo I haue accompliſhed in the ſimple meaſure and maner that you ſee, for the teſtification of my chriſtian affection) or what it may worke in the afflicted party (for whoſe good I doubt not, it was, and is of vs both, in all ſinceritie and ſoundneſſe performed,<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.17.</note> euen as in the ſight of God) I knowe not.</p>
            <p>This I am ſure of, wee be vſed as Gods inſtruments to<note n="r" place="margin">Philip. 2.12.</note> plant and to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but it is he alone,<note n="s" place="margin">1, Cor. 3.6</note> who working in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3223:62"/> vs both the will and the deed according to his good pleaſure, muſt alſo of his ſingular fauor graunt the increaſe,<note n="t" place="margin">1, Cor, 10, 13</note> and with the temptation giue the iſſue alſo, that wee may be able to beare and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, which I beſeeche him heartily, euen for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, as generallie to all his ſaintes, ſo particularlie to that his diſtreſſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that as we haue learned<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 12.15</note> to weep with him in his affliction, ſo in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall feeling of the communion of ſaints, we may learne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with him in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ioy.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Hon. much bounden, and readie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in Ieſus Chriſt. Tho. Wilcockes, the Lordes moſte vnworthe ſeruant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3223:63"/>
            <head>GRACE AND PEACE from God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I cannot but reioyce (good ſir) in your godly loue, and holie care, loue towardes me, that it will pleaſe you to vſe me your poore friend, and one that is and will be readie according to my ſmall abilitie, for anie dutie you ſhall enioyne me: and care towardes your ſelfe, in ſeeking for your ſeke in the middeſt of your troubles and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, ſome Chriſtian comforce and inſtruction, both which are pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e manifeſted, in thoſe two rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rie queſtions that by you in your letter were pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ounded vnto me: ſo I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>what,<note place="margin">Two qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> I muſt confeſſe it, ſeized w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſorowe, partly for that prouiding for my publike p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, lacke of leyſure, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nowe let me, and partlie, for that want of abilitie, to wade into ſuch
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3223:63"/> weightie cauſes ſufficiently, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to deale therein, as gladly I would in reſpect of ſincere affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and as religiouſly I ought, both in regard of the worthineſſe of the cauſes themſelues and of the peace of mine owne heart.</p>
            <p>Howbeit this ſomewhat recomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me that as I reſt perſwaded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you will accept whatſoeuer I ſhall deliuer, ſpeciallie ſith in the ſame I ſhoote at your ſprituall conſolation and good: ſo I hope that God whoſe cauſe it is that I deale in, and whoſe glorie I would gladly, principallie aime at in the ſame, will by his bleſſed ſpirite ſo guide me, that I ſhall propound no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the trueth, from imbracing whereof though you may be ſomewhat hindered, becauſe it is deliuered in a ſimple and meane, both manner and meane, as I my ſelfe denie not, yet let the glory of the trueth it ſelfe (which needeth no mans colours to adorne and bewtifie the ſame) ſo farre preuayle with you, (I beſeech you) that both for
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3223:64"/> iudgement and feeling, it may finde a bleſſed entertainement in you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt of the difference of the feare of the wicked and the feare of the godly.</note>Concerning your firſt queſtion, about the difference that is betwixt the feare of the wicked, and the feare of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſuppoſe it ſhall not be much amiſſe to knowe this, that feare being a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, and ariſing not ſo much from touching,<note place="margin">Natural feare what it is.</note> (for that properly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the body and outward man, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breedeth paine) as from cogitation and thought, which directly concerning the minde and inward man, doth more liuely ſtrike the ſame according vnto which alſo, the bodie it ſelfe (by reaſon of the ſympathie or fellow-feeling, that the one hath with the other) is for the moſt part affected, cannot of it ſelfe, and ſimply conſidered, be vicious and euill. The reaſon wherof is verie plaine and euident, becauſe it being of nature ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: &amp; the ſame infuſed, or put, or pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed into vs, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ration from God, who can not be euill vnleſſe we wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d holde that God made ſome thing euill (which were horrible bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phemie, and quite &amp; cleane
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3223:64"/> contrarie to the fulneſſe of goodneſſe, that is in himſelf, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated vnto all his workes, but ſpecially vnto man.</p>
            <p>I further taking it in it ſelfe, to be no more euill, to haue feare in the heart, than to haue paine in the fleſh: nor that paſſion of feare to be no more ſin in the ſoule, than appetite in the ſtomacke, to eate and drinke, or diſpoſition in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſleepe &amp;c. and ſuch like naturall affections and paſſions.</p>
            <p>Beſides if this and other naturall paſſions, were ſimply and of themſelues faultie, then this would enſue thereupon, that the creatures, ſpeciallie thoſe that we call ſenſitiue (manie of them as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuallie in their kinde feeling this and other paſſions alſo, as man himſelfe) ſhould of themſelues carrie about in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, a lump of iniquitie, which indeed ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be true, both becauſe as in regard of their creation they were good, the<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.3.</note> ſcripture affirming it after Gods own view of them (whoſe iudgement cannot be deceiued) that they were exceedingly good, and alſo becauſe if they had ſinne
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3223:65"/> in themſelues and of themſelues, eyther they muſt haue a reconciler, to paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and them, who alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of their nature, muſt in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that had ſinned ſatiſfie Gods wrath againſt ſinne (but it is too too beaſtly to ſay, eyther that our Sauiour Chriſt had their nature, or that hee dyed for brute beaſtes) or els they muſt of neceſſitie, periſhe vnder condemnation for ſinne, becauſe the<note n="b" place="margin">Rom, 6.23.</note> hier of ſinne in whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, (without a price to ſatiſfie it) is eternall death: and there is no meane we are ſure betweene theſe two.</p>
            <p>But which is moſt notoriouſly euill, abſurd, and erronious aboue all the reſt: Our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, ſhould by this meanes, be polluted with ſame, not onely becauſe according to the ſcriptures, we generally know &amp; beleue that he was<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 2.17, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 15.</note> very man in euery reſpect like vnto vs, (ſinne onely excepted) but alſo becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeaking, euen of this particular huma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie affection in him plainly ſayth, in the Epiſtle to the Hebrues, that hee was<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5, 7.</note> heard in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3223:65"/> thinges which he feared.</p>
            <p>Nowe to ſaie that he was touched or tainted any maner of way, with anie, though neuer ſo ſmall ſpot of ſin, what is it els but to gaineſay the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which in<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 53.9. Ioh. 8, 46. 1 Pet. 2, 22.</note> manie places affirme him, and that moſt rightly, to be voyd of iniquitie? yea to make him no fit ſauior for ſinne, becauſe he that muſt redeeme others from in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quities and tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be himſelfe ſhameleſſe, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he cannot be a price of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? and (which toucheth vs alſo to the quicke, and importeth vs as nigh as life and death) by conſequent to depriue our ſelues of full pardon and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all our ſinnes, becauſe if Chriſt died not the<note n="e" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18,</note> iuſt for the vniuſt, wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnder tranſgreſſion, and being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue<note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ, 2.5.</note> are dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, and ſo vnder eternal death. Here then is required, a right deſerning ſpirite, yea a hart indeede that is indued with a notable portion of heauenly wiſedome &amp; ſpiritual grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue that ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is not of it ſelfe euill (though I ſpeake
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3223:66"/> particularly of the paſſion of feare, yet it ſhall not bee amiſſe to practiſe it in all of the like nature) may thorowe the great worke of the ſanctfiication of the word and ſpirite of God, growe euerie daie better and better, with mightie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes from an high.</p>
            <p>The ſight and knowledge of al which as it cannot but ſtrike muche terror, yea horror into the hearts of the wicked and vngodly, becauſe thorowe the ſtrength and power of their own ſinne, they haue made the light that was in them (which in my minde may not vnfitly be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the dawning of the day, and was and is ſufficient to make them without excuſe or defence before God) to become darkeneſſe, and by that meanes are plunged into obſcuritie as groſſe (if not more groſſe) as that of Egypt: ſo ſhould it be very comfortable to thoſe, in whom the Lord himſelfe hath bene pleaſed by hys owne hand, and ordinaunce to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce that worthie worke of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that not onely while they doe not as the wicked, ſinne in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3223:66"/> of extremitie of naturall paſſions, adding drunkenneſſe vnto thirſt) and thorow the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nature and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans deadly and inſatiable malice, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their own light, and ſo are become ſtocks and voyd of all ſenſe of the ſame: but alſo while they haue nature it ſelf ſo inlightned by the trueth of the word, and reformed by daily addition of grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, that in continuall wreſtling and ſtriuing againſt it, ſpeciallie the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, they gaine ſo much, that they cauſe euen that as other thinges alſo to tend to the aduauncement of his glorie that is Lord of nature, and hath it at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, and to their owne comfort, and the good of others, wherat thoſe ſparks and remainders of nature, that are yet in vs vndefaced, doe in ſome ſorte aime, how much more may they attaine vnto it, not onely when they are accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but when they are ayded thereto, with the graces of God in vs.</p>
            <p>But to come ſomewhat more nigh to the point we are to deale in, and yet it cannot be denied, but that that which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3223:67"/> hath bene alreadie deliuered, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly concerne the ſame methinketh we may betwene the two fe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, which you deſire to be ſatiſfied in, obſerue a double difference: the one as in reſpect of the cauſes, I ſay cauſes, neither let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeeme ſtraunge vnto you, that there are &amp; may be many cauſes of one and the ſelf ſame thing, from whence it commeth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, though ſome in the ſame bee more principall working cauſes, than other, as euerie petie logician wil redily acknowledge) the other as in regard of the effectes and fruites that they bring forth in the ſeuerall parties and perſons diuerſly, (according to the diuerſitie of the feares the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) affected therewith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the feare of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Whence it riſeth.</note>That feare which is in the wicked ariſeth, either from ſome conceite that they haue within them, of ſhame and diſgrace before men, in whoſe ſight, with them themſelues, it is a great and grieuous iudgement, and goeth to their heart, as cold as the panges of death, to be clothed with confuſion, for being men and no more but naturall men, as they
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3223:67"/> like well of themſelues, ſo they woulde gladly be highly eſteemed of their likes:<note place="margin">Groweth.</note> or els, (beeing bitten or ſtoong with the knowledge of ſome euill, eyther conceiued or performed) from ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ſenſe that they haue, of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment before god for the ſame, whoſe infinite iuſtice, as they haue moſte hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly offended, ſo they certainly know, that they cannot by anie meanes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and auoid,<note place="margin">Continueth.</note> this being ingrauen in their heartes by the light of nature that ſinne and his puniſhment muſt alwaies goe, (as it were) arme in arme, or els from ſome other odde imagination, and carnall conceit of their own (as<note n="g" place="margin">Iere. 17.19,</note> mans heart is deceitfull and wicked aboue all thinges, who can knowe it:) and that ſtill in ſelfe loue towardes themſelues onelie, for this neuer moueth them that by their iniquities, they haue pulled wrath and diſpleaſure vpon other men, from almightie GOD: all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one whereof, (no doubt) are muche furthered in them, not onely through abuſe of naturall feare, and alſo by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3223:68"/> meanes of their melancholike conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or complexion, as we ſay (a meane that God himſelfe hath bene pleaſed to appoint and vſe, euen in his iuſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked, greatly to increaſe their terrors and feares) but alſo by the horrible diſtruſtfulneſſe of their owne heartes,<note place="margin">Other cauſes thereof.</note> they finding no matter of true and ſtedfaſt ioy in themſelues (as who in the ſtinging teſtimonie of their owne ſoules, are conuicted of moſte grieuous tranſgreſſions, and eternall iudgement for the ſame, and how is it then poſſible for them to haue ſound peace?) nor ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anie ſure comforte from others, eyther in heauen aboue, or in earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath among men, who if they cannot when, and as they would affoord them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues conſolation, much leſſe may thoſe other looke to receiue it at theyr hands becauſe as in others, ſo in this reſpect charitable reliefe beginneth with a mans owne ſelfe: nor beholding any ioyfull fauour, to them ſelues from God, whoſe diſpleaſure rather in hym ſelfe, and hys creatures, they haue
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3223:68"/> highlie prouoked againſt them, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row infinite iniquities, and therefore muſt looke not onely to haue his backe partes geuen them, but all the veſſels and vials of his wrath in time, and in a full meaſure to bee powred foorth vpon them.</p>
            <p>But the feare of the godlie, is in them not onely as a naturall paſſion (for ſo that condition they haue common wyth the wicked of the world,<note place="margin">Of the feare of the Godly</note> and ſome of the creatures of God,<note place="margin">Where it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</note> as hath in part bene prooued alreadie,) but prooceedeth alſo from an vnfaigned loue, and a ſincere reuerence of God, his maieſtie, and whatſoeuer generallie is in him, &amp; more particularlie his iudgementes,<note place="margin">groweth.</note> beeing ſhead abroade into their heartes, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually planted, continued and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them, thorow the holy exerciſes of his word, and powerfull working of hys bleſſed ſpirit accompanieng the ſame, they beeing alſo ſtyrred vppe thereto, not for worldlye reſpectes or carnall conſiderations,<note place="margin">Continueth</note> as ſhame before men or outward puniſhment that they muſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3223:69"/> vndergoe for ſinne committed, or tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory glorie, which they muſt forgoe and looſe, &amp;c. as the wicked and vngodlie, but vpon holy regardes, euen as wel be ſeemeth Gods ſaintes and ſeruauntes, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onelie profeſſing, but ſincerelie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing godlineſſe: namely, for that they haue ſet God againſt them ſelues, not as a iudge ſharpe and ſeuere, but as a moſt louing &amp; tender father, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce whereof, euen in that reſpect as vnto them, as if it wer the darts of death and the ſenſible feeling for the time, of the verie panges and paines of hell, and the ſtate of the damned, there being litle or no difference betweene the one &amp; the other, but as in regard of length of time, of this life preſent, and the cauſes moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch diſtreſſe: in alſo which they are lead not ſo much to reſpect themſelues (for many of them in vnfeigned loue to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue after a ſort deſired their own deſtruction) as the glorie of God their moſt gracious father, the honour of that bleſſed religion which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and loue of others, that not onely
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3223:69"/> in the fleſh, but alſo in the faith, are deare and precious vnto them, fearing indeede, leaſt all or any of theſe, ſhould in them or by them, bee any manner of way, though neuer ſo ſmallie, wounded or hurte: hauing alwayes, and that in ſuch a portion as God ſeeth fit for his glorie, and their good (notwithſtanding their manifold wantes and vnwoorthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) that pretious gifte of fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, which as it commeth from God alone, and is begun, continued, and encreaſed in his children, by the miniſterie of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, perticipation of the ſacramentes, and powerfull working of his owne ſpirit, ſo is it peculiar to the elect onelie, to appropriate Gods mercies vnto them ſelues, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of their own ſoules, and to ſanctifie as other things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them, ſo this naturall feare within them, and to keepe it in ſo, that it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eake not forth, either into ſinne againſt God, or offence before men. And as concerning the effectes or fruites the which they yeeld and bring foorth (which is the ſeconde difference betweene them,) wee
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3223:70"/> ſhall find as great ods, and diuerſitie as in the cauſes, whereof alſo there is good reaſon, becauſe ſuch as the cauſe is, ſuch is the effecte (which who is it almoſt that knoweth not?) and then the cauſes being ſundrie, the effectes likewiſe muſt be ſo too.</p>
            <p>Concerning the feare that is in the wicked, it either maketh them frefull in themſelues, as we may ſee by that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle quietneſſe they haue, whether they be at home or abroad, ſleep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng or waking in ſickneſſe or in health,<note place="margin">The effects of fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked.</note> their life being nothing els but a ſea of continuall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which fire though they ſeeme for a time to rake vp vnder the aſhes of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt reſt and diſſembled eaſe,<note place="margin">In themſelues</note> yet will it at the length breake foorth as a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie flame to conſume them: or els cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, to be much diſquiet towardes others,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers.</note> they plainely bewraying the ſame either by ſome hard woordes, or ſharpe deedes, or furious countenances, &amp; that many times, not onely againſt them whom they cannot abide, but againſt them alſo that in manifolde reſpectes,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3223:70"/> ſhould be dear vnto them, as their wiues that lie in their boſomes, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r children that iſſue out of their loines, their frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that be as themſelues, their ſeruauntes that haue walked dutifullie towardes them. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Impacience or murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt God.</note> Or prouoketh them to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient and murmuring euen againſt God himſelfe, not only becauſe his hand for ſinne lieth hard &amp; heauy vpon them, but alſo becauſe they can ſee or finde no way, how eyther to ſoften, or to ſhift, or to auoid the ſame. For though they ſeek to run away, &amp; would gladly flie if they could tell how, from the face &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence of his eternal maieſty, (as we may ſee in our firſt<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 3.8</note> parents Adam and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah, and in the practiſe of all ages, and euen of this preſent time) who bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (as it wer) with the teeth, &amp; wounded with the dart of this deadly feare, do not only faint in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and<note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> ſtrike their knees together, but manifeſt to men by ſorrowful ſighes, lamentable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints, yea and deſperate dealings alſo, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times againſt their own ſoules &amp; bodies &amp; that without any remorſe of heart, or
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3223:71"/> godlie griefe at all, whereof wee haue manyfold examples (both in the holye ſcrpitures &amp; other writers alſo) knowne I am ſure vnto you, ſo well exerciſed in the word (as I take and iudge you to be) yet they know there is no way to eſcape his reuenging hand againſt them for their ſinnes, and<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5</note> hart that cannot repent, and that is it that increaſeth their feare, and augmenteth their wo, and cauſeth them to enter into theſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious both wordes and deeds.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Th'effectes of feare in the godly.</note>But the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that is in the godly (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet notwithſtanding mingled, both with hope and ioy, as we may perceiue by the Apoſtles wordes, who ſpeaking of the faithfull-ſaith,<note n="l" place="margin">2. Cor. 4 8</note> We are afflicted on euerie ſide yet are we not in diſtreſſe, we are in doubt, but yet we deſpaire not: and by that which is reported in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, of the women which came to Chriſtes ſepul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, of whom the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſt Matthew affirmeth, that<note n="m" place="margin">Math 28.8.</note> they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parted with fear,<note place="margin">In themſelues</note> &amp; great ioy) maketh them in the daies of their proſperitie (conſidering in what a ticklyſh eſtate<note place="margin">In the daies of proſperitie,</note>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:3223:71"/> they are, and howe eaſily caried into pride, againſt men,<note place="margin">I time of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie,</note> and forgetfulneſſe of God) carefull and watchfull ouer themſelues, ta walke in a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before God and men, according to the meaſure of mercies both paſt and preſent, that they haue receiued from God: and cauſeth them in the midd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of their diſtreſſes (weighing how quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by the remainders of ſince, they may be thruſt into impatienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) to labour the attaining of a quiet ſpirite within themſelues, bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng aſſured, that<note n="n" place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.28</note> all things ſhall worke toge her to the beſt for them that loue and feare God: yea, it prouoketh them, to be humble &amp; low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, yea and that in all ſound maner, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, before whome,<note place="margin">Towardes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they practiſe that, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t alſo for good example, incouragement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort (I meane humblenes of mind proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et heart) that they haue had from others in ſuch like times per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed vnto the themſelues. Ne ther ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it here, but proceedeth further, ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling them according to the grace that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3223:72"/> they haue receiued from God,<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 21.19 What doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes is in the godly.</note> in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to poſſeſſe their owne ſoules before him, in what eſtate or condition ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe him to place them, wherein howſoeuer they be ſometimes ſeized with doubt, not of God verily (whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit power and good wil towards them, they knowe by the trueth of his woord, and particular experience that they them ſelues haue had, to be incomprehenſible and vnchaungeable) but of themſelues by reaſon of the weakneſſe and want which they carrie about with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which alſo by manifold trials in themſelues and others, they haue learned and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, iuſtlie to ſuſpect) yet they haue at the length recourſe vnto him, by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt praier made in faith, and ſo at the laſt are hearde in the thinges that they praied for, according to his will in chriſts obeience being of his ſingular mercie either vtterlie freed from the thinges that they feared, or els hauing ſtrength, patience and comfort communicated vnto them from aboue, to vndergoe and to ouercome a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo (but yet by ſuch
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3223:72"/> holy meanes as God hath appointed, &amp; at ſuch times as he hath ſet with himſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before all times) not only that which preſentlie lieth vpon them, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer afterwardes may pynch, or preſſe downe.</p>
            <p>And this much for this preſent tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this queſtion, wherein I coulde haue willinglie bene contented, further to haue inlarged my ſelfe, but that paper and time ſkanting me, I am conſtrained to finiſh, hoping that whatſoeuer is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting now, may be ſupplied ſome other time hereafter, either by word of mouth, or wryting, or both, as God ſhal be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by you to giue occaſion, and for you and ſome others (to whome I wiſh all good in Ieſus Chriſt) to furniſh mee with abilitie.</p>
            <p>In the meane while I hope this ſhal be wel accepted of you, which whether it be the ſumme of that, that I deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when wee were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt together by word of mouth, and you deſired mee to put downe in writing, I doo not certayneke know: howbeit, the trueth, I
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:3223:73"/> reſt perſwaded, it is: and though it may differ ſomething from it in form and manner, yet I am reſolued that it is the ſame, in ſubſtaunce and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which if perhaps written it affect you not, as when it was ſpoken, lay not the blame thereof vpon your ſelfe (as you are woont to doo) charging yea ſurcharging your ſelfe with dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of comprehenſion: for doubtles God hath giuen you a great grace, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with manye other of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes to conceiue the trueth: neither accuſe the point it ſelfe with darkneſſe and difficultie, for it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the reſt of gods trueth is, plaine and euident vnto them that are inlightned in Sion, but impute the fault of it vnto me, who either tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ignoraunce of the cauſe in my heart cannot, or by reaſon of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or thorow the want of a ſtayed minde perhaps haue not ſo plainely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded my ſelfe, nor waded into the cauſe according to the weight therof, as were to be wiſhed.</p>
            <p>In the diſcourſe whereof, I haue not
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3223:73"/> (as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u ſee) quoted many places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for neither indeede is that my man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, howſoeuer ſome do too much affect it (vnleſſe ſome vrgent c uſe, or the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſt of my good friendes drawe me thereto) neyther thinke I that the trueth ſtandeth ſo much vpon the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of allegations or wordes of text it ſelfe, as vpon ſound reaſons deduced from the ſame.</p>
            <p>But if happilie you are deſirous to ſee ſentences of ſcriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for theſe pointes, you may looke vpon the Concordances and tables th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready publiſhed vpon the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de and new Teſtament, which in the tytle of Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re will affoord you ſtore, whether alſo for breuities ſake, I ſende you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe them, at your leyſure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd at your pleaſure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s you ſhall thinke good.</p>
            <p>One or two pointes, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th places out of the woord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s my memorie would helpe, I cou d not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is written before le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, as this firſt, that feare is not cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to ſaith &amp; hope, which is prooued Phil p. 2.11.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3223:74"/> Hebrues 3.14. 1. Peter. 3.17. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that God by his worde,<note place="margin">Godly feare not contrary to faith.</note> hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men, ſundrie good meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue it, and amongeſt the reſt, theſe, as minding of Gods former fauours, for which ſee Deut. 7.18.19.20. earneſt prayer and calling vppon his name, for which ſee,<note place="margin">Meanes to remoue the griefe of feare.</note> Geniſ. 32.7.9.13. Thirdly that the feare of the faithfull, is ſo farre from bringing miſeries with it, that it hath attending vpon it, as an vnſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companion, bleſſedneſſe from God, for which ſee, Prouerb. 28.14.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond queſtion of the boldneſſe of the wicked and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>Touching your ſecond queſtion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ference that is betwixt the boldneſſe of the godly, &amp; that which the wicked ſeeme to haue, I truſt (the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſes conſidered) I ſhall not neede to ſpend labour, or take anie pain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, becauſe theſe thinges beeing one of them contrarie to the other, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being oppoſed (as we ſaie) doe more plainly appeare, they may be an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewe (as it were) and by comparing them one with another, bee eaſily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:3223:74"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, if you ſhall not thinke this ſufficient, doe but ſignifie ſo much in a line or two, and you ſhal (God willing) with conuenient ſpeede, heare from me.</p>
            <p>And ſo hoping that you wil aſſiſt me, with your heartie prayers vnto the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, not onely for a ſanctified vſe of ſuch fauours as I haue receiued, but for a bleſſed continuance and mightie increaſe of the ſame, for the glory of him that giueth them, for the peace of myne owne heart, for the profite of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and amongeſt them for your good: I take my leaue haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. At Broingdon, the 24. of this Decemb. 1588.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours aſſured and readie alwaies in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, Thomas VVilcocks, the Lordes vnworthie ſeruant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:75"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>I beſeech thee (good reader) pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ſcapes committed, &amp; amend with thy pen, theſe faults following, or whatſoeuer thou, according to the iudgment and light that thou haſt receiued, ſhalt find amiſſe herein.</p>
            <p>Pag. 1. line 17. for explicat, read commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate. pag. 4. line, 25. for world, read word. Pag. 8. line 10. l. read he. pag. 13, line, 10. for irrepugnable, read impregnable. pag. 19. lin. 3. meanes. read mercies. pag. 36. line 19. comforts, read comforters. pag. 48. line 8. repent, read repenteth. pag. 49 line 19. after works, adde, and. pag. 50. line 5. after it, add might, and line 14. for euamate, euacuat. Pag. 51. line 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. for make Ieſus, read ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this. pag. 54. line 4. for our, read one. pag. 55. line 26. put out alwaies. pag 61. line 10. for him, read them. pag. 62 line 4. put out as, and line 8. for for, read ſee. pag. 63. line 22 after therefore, adde neede pag. 64. line 8. for tyrannie, read turning. 19. for caſt, read coſt. and line 20. for peece, read price. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 66. line 13. would, read could. pag. 67. line 6. naturally, read naturall. pag. 68. line 8 after ſpirite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, adde, and. pag 70. line 1. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto, adde you. pag. 74. line 9. for 1589. read 1579. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g. 89. line 6. for might, read we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh. pag. 96, line <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. for expectation, read exception, line 15. for neither ſhall neuer turn, nor ſhaddowe by turning. pag 98, line 10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead work, pa. 100. lin, 1. for to, read both. pag 108. line 9, for ſelfe, read li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3223:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
